[music]
Heat.
[music] Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Hello and welcome to the Ask Bijit Show.
This is a special episode. I hope you're
all doing great. Let me see who all is
there in the live stream with us in the
live chat. I can see Animeish
Somalia Paul
who says why this episode? Well, why
this episode? Why today today I think
it's Wednesday is it? It's a Wednesday.
I'm traveling this weekend. I will not
be available to do a live stream this
weekend and that's why I thought that I
will do a special session just uh to
offset my absence on for the over the
weekend. I'm traveling to Jaipur for the
Jaipur dialogues and if any of you are
going to be in Jaipur I will be very
very pleased to meet you there. Right.
So that's the reason why I am u doing
this special episode. So let's see who
else who else we have. I have Somi Jane
who is here from Japur good to see you.
Pearl Gupta thank you very much. Nilles
Shivastav Mr. Jam Mar Kane good to see
you ma'am. Mar Kane Aman Patana from
Melbourne Aush Singh Reanir Ratura
Painter uh Suman Shaker Saringi Adimish
Adi Aayou Ritik Sasmith Adi Aayou once
again Stone Hush says yo yo yo Ritik
imagine spacetime Mr. Jam I'm a painter.
Happy birthday. Well, well, thank you so
much. Thank you to everyone who has
wished me a happy birthday. It's not yet
a belated birthday. My h my birthday is
uh it's a fourthcoming birthday. It will
it's it's tomorrow. So anyway, thank you
everyone. Uh who else do we have?
Ashwani Swami Jane
um Himmanu Rajpur Hit Querty Q123 Sush
Atarvatakur Vortex Abhishek Shukla from
Kpur Rahul Himani from Mumbai
Sumanjarangi Mitun SP Namaste Makavin
good to see you Ashwani versatile feel
strong man hello Narada hello Rahul Das
Aal Biju Narita Das good to see you good
to see you as
Himach abhijijit chav light well that's
quite a name Gupta is from Jaipur all
right good to see you sir stone
sudhanchu sodager ram David kundu hello
adwe hello uh Shivven singer
um Sumit Agarwal my English accent is
not typical for India well yeah I know
that Manisha Kardoso uh thank you very
much ma'am thank you uh Atarvatakur
Alvin Rodriguez imagine Spacetime is an
astrophysicist. Good to see you. Good to
have an astrophysicist on board. Very
good to see you. Imagine spacetime. Sai
Nurup from Hyderabad. Good to see you as
well. Namaste. Uh Capil Lad Himman Shu
from Chennai. Namita Das. Ain
uh Kai Artsy Weeb Juraj. Good morning.
Well, good morning to you as well. Abida
Singh Ayata.
Uh Priyanka Javalia. Good evening ma'am.
found me on the 17th of April 2021
through Reanir Alabadia. Well, it was a
good day. [laughter] Thank you so much,
ma'am. Good to have you. Canel dire.
Hello, James. My good friend James is
here. Always good to have you, James. I
appreciate you, James. Uh, geopolitical
dub, namaste, jam, hers,
thank you very much. Anoj Basin,
Prashant Panar, Atarvatakur,
uh, Soldier Boy and everyone else. Okay,
now Gez,
what's up? Manua, hello. Bruce Wayne is
also here. Trader insight, Adita. Okay,
let's uh stop greeting everybody
otherwise it'll go on all day. Darbam
from Hyderabad, hello. Bhargavi, good,
good evening and everyone else. Okay, so
now let's take questions. I'm going to
take questions that you all have asked
in the comments for a change. I usually
do geopolitics live streams with super
chats. Today I will do it from the
questions you've asked in the comments.
So what's the qu first question for
today? I've selected 20 questions.
Hopefully we can go through all of those
and if there is still time I'll take
some questions from the live chat as
well. But let's begin with the questions
I've I've selected from the comments.
What's question one?
Anonymous scientist says the India and
the US have extended their 10-year
defense agreement.
Will the US force it to use it to force
India to purchase F-35s which are trash?
But they aren't exactly trash. They're
superb aircraft but uh they're not that
great either. Okay. So is this agreement
a gimmick or does India actually get
something beneficial from this
agreement? So I have tried and attempted
to locate the full text of the agreement
but it's not available um in the public
domain. So it's an agreement that the
two nations have signed but they have
not released the text. I mean the last
time I tried to find it I was unable to
find the text. uh but we know kind of
what the press releases have been like
and what has been uh communicated to the
public. So this agreement was signed
just a few days ago and um what is it
all about? It's about so there's there
some broad you know broad aspects that
have been agreed upon and I'm sure there
are details that you can drill down in.
One is the two nations will continue
their technological cooperation, their
industrial cooperation and collaboration
that will continue the two nations will
continue to u do sharing you know engage
in sharing of information and
intelligence right so that will continue
to whatever extent it was continuing I'm
not sure if there's going to be
enhancement of that but it's going to
continue then there's going to be the
continuation of military
interoperability
there's going to be the continuation of
various kinds of joint exercises that
happen a few times a year that will
continue. Uh there's also reference to
the Indo-Pacific that so the two nations
have agreed that they are committed to
their joint um you know to to
maintaining uh open and free and
rules-based Indo-Pacific region and
rules-based world order which Donald
Trump is actively appending but yeah
sure okay right um and the yeah so that
sort of thing you know free and open
navigation of the Indo-acific region um
we will oppose any coercive actions
you know we will reinforce deterrence
and we we we seek stability of the
Indopacific that sort of you know
verbage has been used and apparently
there's a long-term road map for for
collaboration and the two gentlemen who
signed the agreement uh that is India's
defense minister Mr. Rajnat Singh and
the US Secretary for War Pete Hexath
they have said that this agreement this
this extension of the agreement it
repres represents some kind of new era
in the relationship between the two
countries and it's um it's vital for
ensuring regional stability and the
rules based international order. So
that's what I have gleaned from whatever
I have seen. I'm sure there is more that
I've missed but I don't have the text or
or the summary or whatever in front of
me. So that's essentially what it is. So
now the question is is this just a
gimmick? Okay. Will the US use this
agreement to force India to purchase
those F-35s that we don't don't want? Um
does India actually get something
beneficial from this agreement? I think
this agreement this extension of the
agreement it it sets a baseline in the
relationship between the two nations.
The relationship has been nosediving uh
for the past several months.
The US has imposed u extremely heavy you
know sanctions tariffs on India 50%
despite India purchasing less Russian
oil than China significantly less
Russian oil now than China but China
gets a significant relaxation on of
tariffs but India does not so that is
that's one issue the other issue is that
the US is adopting a maximalist approach
when it comes to the trade negotiations
for the whenever the trade deal happens
which is not happening right now right
there is And obviously the the biggest
issue is that the Americans are openly
taking the side of Pakistan you know
blatantly and um all of that and they
are going ahead with all kinds of
investments in Pakistan and they are
selling you know various missiles and
whatn not to Pakistan the Saudi Pakistan
deal all of that so India US
relationships the relations are nosed so
this agreement seems to be something
that sets a baseline that we can
maintain right I don't see India getting
anything significantly beneficial from
commit beyond whatever we already have
the kind of relationship we already
have. Um is it a gimmick? It's not a
gimmick. It's like you know it's setting
a bottom on the relationship. So it
won't go be below this that sort of
thing. And uh it will set some kind of
framework by through which the two
nations can can you know continue the
relationship you know you have various
domains in which you have relations with
the nation. The defense domain, the
economic domain, trade, finance,
whatever else. So this is one aspect of
that. Will the US uh use this deal to
force India to purchase F-35s? They
can't force us to do anything. The F-35s
will come with all kinds of strings
attached that I have gone into in great
detail. And that will have the effect of
undermining the sovereignty of any
nation that purchases the F-35. And it's
not even that great of an aircraft.
Obviously, it's a fifth generation
fighter plane. No question about it.
It's superior to anything India
currently has. But it's it's not a good
deal for India. The US can't force India
to purchase those F-35s. They can't. So
I don't see that happening. I I think
the day the Indian India purchases F-35s
is the day we will officially have
announced that we have given up our
sovereignty. Essentially that's what it
means. So I don't see that happening and
I hope that I'm absolutely 100% correct
on this matter about the F-35s. Okay,
next question.
Okay. Ass an anonymous scientist. Uh,
how do you see Trump accusing Pakistan
of secretly testing nuclear weapons? Is
the US not happy with its vasal state
Pakistan or is it just a public stunt?
The US has accused North Korea, China,
Russia also of doing the same thing. And
Trump has justified his decision to
restart nuclear tests by saying
Pakistan, China etc. are doing it. So is
Pakistan testing nukes, earthquakes in
Pakistan after operation sindur. Where
these nuclear tests? Okay. Okay. So the
big question over here is Trump has gone
ahead and said claimed disclosed
essentially that Pakistan and China also
apparently have been conducting uh super
critical nuclear tests. So what is this
criticality? What is subcritical? What's
super critical? So see in nuclear
weapons advanced designs you have
chemical explosives that set off a
series of u events inside the nuclear
weapon that eventually culminates with
the fish or fish and fusion reaction
that gives off the output that the
nuclear device gives you. Right? So the
initial the trigger is a is an explosion
through chemical explosives and then you
need to have a certain geometry and all
that through which the you know various
uh subcritical masses nuclear masses
they they come together and uh set off
the fish reaction that may only be a
fish reaction or may set off a secondary
fusion reaction etc etc we'll not go
into the engineering. So you can test
nuclear weapons design by just igniting
the chemical explosives and not having
actual nuclear fuel in there. So that's
a subcritical test. Essentially a super
critical test is one in which the
nuclear fuel ignites.
You have a fishision or fusion or both
kind of reaction. So the you know
there's a global moratorium right now in
place that no one's going to conduct
nuclear tests and as part of this
moratorium you are allowed to do
subcritical text tests
so Trump is saying that China and
Pakistan Pakistan and China are doing
supercritical tests nuclear tests which
is actual nuclear explosions right and
he says that you know they drill very
deep underground so that you know just
get some mild vibrations and so on
that's what he has claiming that's what
he has claimed that's what essentially
he's disclosed the US president has
disclosed see when the president of the
United States says something you cannot
take it lightly you have to take it very
seriously
so he has disclosed that Pakistan has
been conducting nuclear tests and he's
also said China is doing it maybe even
Russia I'm not sure so then the question
is what about those earthquakes that
were detected in the around the time of
operation zindu the three-day war uh May
719 around that
8 9 whichever the dates were and even
after that event when the operation was
paused there have been more um seismic
events in Pakistan u a cluster of these
uh happened in Balojasthan Pakistan
occupan and a bunch of these happened in
Pakistan occupied Punjab
so what were these things so I went
ahead I think once I did it live on this
show and I I showed you that you know
These some of these earthquakes uh their
their origin is about 10 12 kilometers
underground sometimes even 100 km
underground.
Now the deepest hole that any human you
know any that human beings have have
drilled it's in the vicinity of like 10
11 kilo kilometers deep. It's very
difficult to drill holes that are that
deep.
So does Pakistan have the engineering
capability to to drill 10 kilometer deep
holes just for nuclear tests? I doubt it
very much. Essentially they don't have
it. Then what's the deal? The deal. But
Trump is claiming they have been doing
nuclear tests. What's [snorts] it mean?
It could very well mean that this data
that's available in the public domain,
it's falsified data. Maybe the nuclear
the test happened only 500 kilometers
down maybe 1 kilometer down but it is
being shown as something that's 10 12 15
whatever kilometers down you know these
uh agencies or organizations that put
out this data they can very well falsify
it it's not the Indian government that's
putting it out it's uh these this data
essentially comes from western agencies
and organizations so it's possible that
they may be falsifying it and claiming
it's 10 12 15 km down when it's actually
just maybe maybe perhaps just half a
kilometer down, maybe a kilometer down.
That's possible. You can't trust all
this information that's out there, all
this data that's put out in the public
domain. You can't trust it. You can't
I'm not saying it's all f it's all
false. But some of it can be selectively
falsified. Understand that. I'm sure the
government of India also has its seismic
detectors and whatever else is required.
And I'm sure they're aware of it. But
they will not go ahead. The government
of India will not go ahead and disclose
this in public. Trump has done it. Very
good. Fantastic.
So it's possible that the Pakistanis
were testing some nuclear devices. It's
possible. Now the question is these
nuclear devices who owns these
has Pakistan actually developed nuclear
weapons or are these nuclear weapons
simply devices that have been given to
them on loan by somebody?
I doubt very much that the Pakistani
nuclear scientists have the capability
to develop a full-fledged nuclear
weapons program. Maybe look, it's not
that difficult actually. Okay. All you
need is file material, uranium, a
certain quantity of uranium and I think
any half decent engineer can rig a
device that will you know implode two
subcritical masses of of uranium and
make them super critical and you will
have some kind of an explosion. So I'm
sure the Pakistanis tested some nuclear
devices in 1998 or whenever it was. But
I expect I'm I'm pretty sure that the
devices they have today are not theirs.
Maybe maybe somebody else has given
these devices on loan. Most likely the
United States. So if the Pakistanis were
testing weapons,
did the Americans give them the the
green light to do that? See first of all
if these devices are American devices
then I can assure you that just like the
like the case with the UK the
[clears throat] big red button does not
sit in Rahul India or Islamabad it sits
somewhere else.
So if the tests happen maybe it's the
Americans who have tested this. There's
all kinds of options open. I doubt very
much if Pakistan if it does have nuclear
weapons it I doubt that they have
sovereignty over those. most likely they
are just placed in Pakistani territory
for counterbalancing purposes visav
India maybe even some other country.
Uh so if Trump has made a disclosure
that Pakistan has been testing nuclear
weapons we have to take it very
seriously. Trump has this uh this track
record of saying all kinds of things
some of which or many of which may not
be entirely correct but in this case we
have to take him very seriously. The
government of India has to take him very
very seriously.
Um so so does it mean the Americans are
unhappy with Pakistan their vasal state?
Why have they accused Pakistan of doing
this? And you will see that Pakistan has
not responded at all to this claim by
Trump to this disclosure by Trump. See
if Trump had made a statement about
India. India would have immediately gone
ahead and made a public statement either
confirming or denying what what Trump
said. Pakistan hasn't done that. They
have been quiet. What does it mean? Is
the US unhappy with Pakistan? No. The US
is very pleased with Pakistan.
Pakistan is an obedient lap dog.
Sometimes you beat up the lap dog and
the lap dog still comes to you and does
what you say. So it's just the US wants
to restart nuclear weapons testing. So
they want to take some names. See, China
is the adversary. Russia is also a big
adversary. But Pakistan is a loyal lap
dog right now because you know it's
under leash. It's leashed right now. So
that's why they have also thrown
Pakistan with you know this accusation
of Pakistan then Pakistan will just take
it Pakistan will not say a word against
to against Trump. So that's the deal.
Okay. Further about the nuclear uh deal
Swami and Rushab Dare why is the US
talking about testing nuclear weapons?
What does the country gain by testing
them repeatedly? Uh is it information?
Is it checking that they are working
just fine or something else? My thoughts
on Trump's announcement to restart
nuclear tests. Is it in response to the
burst burthnic
missile test by Russia, an escalation of
war in Ukraine along with the continuous
rise of China, or do they truly want to
start a nuclear age like they did in the
cold war by dropping nukes on Japan?
Well, the dropping nukes on Japan
happened before the cold war. And but
anyway, so why is the US talking about
testing nuclear weapons? has Trump
announced that he's going to that the US
is going to resume testing nuclear
weapons. Why is that?
Look, nuclear weapons have to be tested.
Any weapons that you have have to be
tested to validate the design to
validate that it's working fine to find
flaws and defects in in those weapons
and then you rectify that and test again
to see if the flaw is now been been
fixed. Maybe you want a certain amount
of yield in terms of kilot in terms of
kilotons of TNT or megat tons of TNT but
maybe it's not exactly the yield is not
what you expect maybe it's too little
maybe it's too too much so you want to
fine-tune the weapon for these things
you have to test it right so the last
when did the last nuclear weapons test
happen 1998 India after that North Korea
has been testing nuclear weapons uh
France tested sometime in the 1990s and
the US tested some time ago the Russians
Soviets Russians tested before that. So
it's been like 30 or so years since the
west has tested nuclear weapons and
maybe they have come up with more
advanced designs that they can that they
can you know kind of do some modeling
through supercomputers and whatnot but
you actually at the end of the day you
have to actually test it out. So maybe
the US decid has decided that it's time
to test out the new designs and test
that the old ones are still working as
we expect. Makes sense. Makes sense. But
you can't just start testing just like
that unilaterally. So you have you have
to invent a just cause for whatever
action you're going to take. If the
action is very potentially
destabilizing, you need to you know
justify. So that's why they are blaming
other countries. Maybe the maybe China,
Russia, Pakistan are actually testing
it. It's very possible if the US
president says that we have to take it
seriously. So what does the country gain
by testing nuclear weapons? Not
repeatedly. It's been 30 30 or so years.
It's been a long gap. It makes sense to
test them now. It's been too long since
you tested.
>> Whatever weapons you have, you have to
keep them, keep on testing them
periodically. India conducts missile
tests periodically, doesn't it? Even the
old missiles like the pursu missiles and
the older missiles, we test them once or
twice a year just to ensure you take a
random missile out of the stockpile and
you test it. So they you know that you
know statistically everything is working
fine. So the US obviously it makes sense
for them to test nuclear weapons. It's
been a long time since any any of these
were tested. So it looks like Trump has
decided that now is the time or maybe he
has been given the advice that now is
the time to resume nuclear testing.
So it's not like they are trying to
escalate something. Is it in response to
the Burvetnik missile test? No, it's not
that the Burvatnik is a missile. It's
not a nuclear weapon. It is a missile
that is nuclear capable. It can carry a
nuclear warhead and it's a
nuclearpropelled missile. Okay, it most
likely has a nuclearpowered ramjet
engine. So the propulsion itself is
nuclear which gives it theoretically
unlimited range. It can fly for months.
It can even be recalled without actually
hitting a target. That's the deal with
the Burvatnik missile. So that obviously
is something that the US currently
doesn't have. They had something called
Project Pluto or something in the 1960s,
but they shelved it. Maybe it was seen
as too provocative. Maybe it was seen as
not necessary once the ballistic
missiles of the US became sufficiently
uh accurate.
Um so the US isn't isn't trying to start
a nuclear age. We are already in the
nuclear age. So many nations like eight
nine nations have nuclear weapons. So
the US just wants to test maybe it's
newer designs, maybe test the validity
of the older designs and they are okay
if other countries follow suit because
if the US tests I assure you Russia will
test, China also will most likely test
and there's a moderate probability that
India will also test. Makes sense for
India to test. So that's the deal and I
would say that if the US tests, India
should also go ahead and test uh
whatever needs to be tested because see
we tested in 1998. I'm sure we have
enhanced those designs.
That's 27 years ago that we tested by
those nuclear weapons that we tested at
that time. I'm sure we have far more
advanced nuclear weapons designs today,
but those have not been tested. Right?
So, if the US tests, it makes a lot of
sense for us to validate our own nuclear
weapons designs, the new ones. And how
do you do that? You do it by testing
those.
Raj Akash Kumar says Trump said the US
needs to test nuclear weapons as
Pakistan and China and other countries
are doing it. Okay. So that the reply to
Russia for the nuclear fuel missile
Burvetnik and will Russia and India
start their nuclear tests. Currently
India is conducting operation thrishul
army navy air force are all doing
practice operations in various parts of
India several parts of India and
yesterday ISRO launched a heavy
communications satellite. What's
cooking?
First of all, the uh let's talk about
ISRO, the ISRO angle. ISRO couple of
days ago launched uh the heaviest
communication satellite we've launched
indigenously, right? Uh is it somehow
related to all of this? I do not think
so. See,
when you launch a heavy communication
satellite, that satellite has to be
constructed. You cannot put it together
in two days. Takes a few months to put
it together. There are lots of different
agencies involved in building
communication satellite which
essentially is a you could say a
military satellite, naval satellite.
Yeah. And uh so you need to do all of
that. You need to integrate it with the
with the fairing of the of the rocket.
You have to do stress testing, vibration
testing. And the rocket itself has to be
put together. Is IS is not like SpaceX
that we have 20 rockets just that just
need to be assembled in two days and
we're good to go. No, IRO I think it's
building every rocket on demand.
If you go to SpaceX headquarters, you
will see like 50 rockets just lying
around in in a properly designated area
and those can be very rapidly put
together and launched because they're
launching like a rocket a week, right?
And they have reusable rockets and
whatnot. ISO is not like that. So this
rocket launch, this satellite launch
that must have been planned months in
advance,
right? So it's it's not in response to
what's happening. First of all, we have
to understand that. Now operation thrish
is very interesting, right? that's going
on and it's been announced very recently
and army, navy, air force, everyone's
involved in that. There are various note
times that have been issued notice to
airmen where you know we giving a
warning that we are conducting live
firing exercises and military exercises
in in this area everyone civilian
traffic commercial traffic stay out if
something happens it's not our fault we
are we are giving you a warning in
advance that's a noam so multiple notams
have been issued um so is operation
thrishul in response to what's happening
here you know the nuclear issue the
Pakistan issue the fact that operation
Synindhur is paused. It is not ended. It
could resume. Operation Threshul is very
interesting. Maybe it is a statement,
maybe it is a statement not just to
Pakistan. Pakistan doesn't matter. Maybe
it's a statement to Pakistan's master or
masters that you know what we are fully
ready. Uh
it's also possible that India may be
preparing to if required conduct nuclear
weapons tests. It's also possible. Look,
I am not putting out any classified
information in the public domain. This
is just speculation. Okay? But it's also
possible that if the US tests, we should
be ready to test immediately before the
US can say, you know what, nobody else
test and you're not allowed to. If they
test and we find out through our seismic
detectors, then we should immediately
test. So maybe that's also part of
what's happening. Maybe operation
threshold is part of the readiness for
maybe a nuclear weapons test if
required. We will not be able to test
nuclear weapons without the US first
testing them. If we go ahead and
unilaterally test nuclear weapons, the
Americans will impose sanctions on us.
No question about it. The West
collectively will impose various
sanctions on us. But if the US tests
first and then we go ahead and say that
you know what if you're testing big big
brother we could also test then it'll be
you know it will make less sense for
them to it will give them less
justification to impose sanctions on us.
So I would say that maybe we are getting
ready for all kinds of things right now.
There's the Pakistan issue angle. Uh
operation zindur it's been several
months now and the longer we wait the
stronger Pakistan gets because it is
going to get supplies
arms ammunition weapons systems all of
that from the west from Saudi Arabia is
going to be able to reugment its
defenses. So the longer we wait the less
advantageous it is for us. So maybe
something is brewing, maybe nothing is
brewing. I have no idea. But yeah, it's
interesting that this very large scale
set of uh military exercises is is being
conducted right now by by us by India.
Okay, multiple questions about the Quad.
Amisha says, uh sorry, Abhinav says if
India is replaced by the Philippines in
the Quad, will it be a significant
victory for China? Amisha says, what are
your predictions for for the Quad? Uh,
will the Quad come back to relevance or
is the Quad in coma now? Somi says, "How
do you see India being dethroned by the
Philippines in the Quad? What does the
US gain from it? It is practically a
coalition of the US and its vasals. Why
form such a group that has no value? Has
the US accepted that China is is a new
hedgeim?" And geopolitical Dubai says,
"Does the Quad hold no relevance
anymore? How can the Philippines replace
Barat in the region? Does the US no
longer see bat as necessary to counter
China? Okay. Quad.
I'm sure you are all aware of something
called SARKC, the so-called South Asian
Association of for Regional Cooperation.
When was the last time there was a SARKC
summit? Roughly a decade ago, right?
SARKC
is defunct today. It still exists on
paper,
but it's no longer active. Why is it not
active? because we killed it. If if a
sark summit is organized and we don't
turn up, SAC is finished, right? India
is the major nation in SAK.
>> The Pakistanis and the Bangladeshes can
hold a you know so-called SAK summit,
but if India is not present, it's over.
So SARKC has been killed off by us.
Similarly,
the Quad still exists on paper, but uh
it won't continue. It it it like like
Amisha says, it's kind of going to be in
coma just like SARKC is. So what has
happened? Has India been replaced by the
Philippines in the quad? Has India been
dethroned by the Philippines? So first
of all, the US hasn't said any no one
has said that in the Quad we are
removing India and we're putting
Philippines there. No such statement has
been made. Right? So now the US is
creating a new kind of alignment. the
US, Japan, the Philippines, maybe
Australia is part of that and whoever
else. So it's kind of like a
substitution for India and the Quad and
it's a new bunch of nations that comes
up. Now understand, was India given a
throne when we were in the quad? Was
being in the quad something of great
prestige and great value to us? Was it
like wearing a crown? Was it like
sitting in a throne? It wasn't.
What was the
why did the quad exist? The quad existed
to uh counterbalance China's hegemonic
imperialistic activities in the
Indo-Pacific region, the South China Sea
region and overall the Asia Asia Pacific
region. Right? That's why the US two of
its vasals Japan and Australia came
together and we also got added to that
because it made sense for us also to
[snorts] be part of such a grouping so
that we could you know so
India's number one threat threat if you
look at our threat perception our threat
horizon the major challenge the major
threat for India is China which is about
three four times more powerful than
India overall right and China has been a
very hostile nation
We know the history. I don't need to go
back into into the history. I don't need
to retell the history [clears throat]
between India and China. And China has
been the aggressor. India has never
provoked China. And China still claims
Indian territory. And China continues
its u you know infrastructure building
activities in Chinese occupied Tibet and
whatnot. So India clearly faces a threat
threat and if you have nations like the
US, Australia, Japan that that you can
team up with to counter the Chinese
threat then it makes sense and that's
why India was part of the quad after all
the incidents that happened in the past
decade in the 2010s the Doluti incident
the um whatever else in incidents uh the
the the Galwan incident which was very
which was very bad and so on. So made
sense for India to be part of that
grouping. But now things have changed
significantly. The US now is piling on
the pressure on India. The relationship
has no dived right. The US is taking the
side of Pakistan. Pakistan no longer has
China as big daddy. Pakistan has slipped
out of China's graasp
and and it's in the US lap now today. So
things have changed not just for India
for China also.
And so now India and China seem seem to
be having some kind of some kind of
course we are not blindly trusting
anything. We understand what China
represents but we are taking it very
cautiously and as such now that the US
is treating India as an adversary now
that the US seeks to contain India very
openly and overtly and also China and
also China that's why India China and
Russia seem to be on the same boat now
so it makes no sense for India to
continue its squad activities
right the quad is dead the Americans
killed quad we didn't kill the quad and
when we were in the quad it was not like
we were sitting on a throne where the
Americans simply saw one utility for
India that was as a counterbalance to
China and India was not enough to
counterbalance China that's why they
they enlisted Japan and Australia as
well in the matter
so so essentially the US regarded India
even at that time as a pawn on the
geopolitical chess board it was not a
gesture of friendship it was a matter of
convenience
so we have not been rethrown by the
Philippines. The Philippines cannot
replace India but India is now an
adversary for the US. That's how they
see us. We don't see them as an
adversary. We would like to continue the
cooperation, the collaboration, the good
relationship, the excellent relationship
that we had and we would like to make it
even better but they see it differently
and it makes sense strategically from
their perspective. So things have
changed. Has the US accepted China as as
a new hedgeim? They have kind of tacitly
accepted that China is now the hgemon in
the eastern hemisphere kind of they have
done that right so the Philippines has
not replaced Barat the equations have
changed the quad is now on on ice it's
on cold it's in cold storage and it most
likely won't be revived for for the
foreseeable future if ever so the US is
now exploring a different set of uh
geopolitical alignments and equations
and that's where the Philippines comes
in the US uh has essentially kind of you
could say given up the eastern
hemisphere to China right it would the
US would still very much want India they
would still like very much India to
become its vasal but that's not showing
any signs of happening unless there is
some kind of a change in New Delhi which
the US would like to engineer well
that's a whole different story so that
is the deal with the quad the quad still
exists but it is on ice it is in cold
storage it is in a kuma like Abisha says
and This Philippines thing is a whole
different entity. It's a different
alignment, different grouping.
Yashard Tiwari says, "The chaos that's
happening around the world, is it a sign
of world war going to happen in in in
the near future?" McLeven says, "India
has issued multiple NOTAMs from November
all the way to January, conducting six
major military exercises simultaneously.
Pakistan has also issued a notam and
Pakistan is allegedly receiving weapons
deliveries from the United States. Yeah.
Missiles and whatnot. AM, RAM and so on.
Whatever. Bangladesh is receiving
weapons and defense systems from Turkey.
The US is also involved in Bangladesh as
we know very well. Trump has ordered his
uh he has ordered the resumption of
nuclear testing in the US. Central banks
across the world have started buying a
lot of gold recently. Does all these
factors indicate do all these factors
indicate that we are preparing for a
world war? We are preparing. We are
going to This is most likely the
indication that there's going to be a
tremendous amount of global upheaval,
turmoil and instability. We are seeing a
situation in Sudan facing Africa being
destabilized.
We have Ukraine going on. There is the
Hamas Gaza issue that is kind of
simmering down now. And there are other
issues. There's the India Pakistan thing
that has flared up now, right? And so
much more. So this is a sign that the
world order is is changing very rapidly
and um it does not necessarily indicate
a world war that will come up very soon.
The US and China none of the major
nations wants a world war.
That's
okay. We're back.
Brief glitch. So the point is nobody
wants a world war. If there's a world
war, it will ruin everyone including the
US, including China, Russia, India, and
everybody else. It will not just ruin
everyone, it will destroy the world. No
one wants that. What we're going to see
is geoeconomic turmoil. We're going to
see maybe multiple clashes at various
flash points, you know, that that could
erupt. That could happen. And when you
have so much instability that you
foresee on the horizon, especially
geoeconomic
uh instability, what do you do? You go
for gold. Gold is the only uh store of
value, economic value that is, you know,
that is bankable essentially long term.
Uh so when you foresee a recession, when
you foresee geopolitical ge geoeconomic
instability, when you foresee
potentially chaos in the world, banks,
major central banks will start buying up
a lot of gold. Right? So we are seeing
the decoupling essentially of the world
order. We're going to we're seeing the
the emergence of the new cold war. The
battle lines of the cold war are being
drawn. India is still you know the US
still would like India to be on their
side but maybe India will be drawn into
our IC which will be a very strange and
very new kind of grouping for us to be
in. It will potentially quite
uncomfortable and we'll have to see how
how to navigate that.
Um and so on. So the US is obviously
encircling India. It is it seeks to
contain India. Why? East Pakistan, West
Pakistan, maybe project Kokan for
Christ, maybe so much more. All of that
is happening. This doesn't necessarily
indicate a world war. It indicates a
bifurcation of the world order. The US
doesn't want a multipolar world order.
Neither does China.
So there's going to be instability as as
the glo the world order bifurcates. And
everyone's going to have to make a
choice which side you're on. Are you on
the western side or the eastern side?
And if you're on whatever side you have
to perhaps accept someone as your
overlord, as your as your hegeimon, as
your susarin, [clears throat] right?
Maybe India may also be forced to make
tough choices at some point in time. So
that's a situation we are expecting
instability, increased instability,
maybe recession, maybe maybe multiple
flash points, you know, breaking out
into localized wars. Hopefully not more
than that.
Uh and that's why we are seeing all the
major central banks buying up a lot of
gold. So hopefully no world war. That's
the last thing we want, but definitely
instability.
Ryik RPG says in Trump's post stating
that the G2 will be convening shortly.
Is he signaling a shift in how the
United States views its relationship
with China? potentially treating China
more as an equal partner rather than a
junior or rival partner and sh says is a
bipolar world order inevitable with two
poles US and China will India and Russia
becomes of China given that the level of
technological advancements China are
doing uh which will make Chinese
military extremely superior compared to
India and Russia
right so Trump said that G2 will be
convening shortly the Chinese made no
such statements but there's been this
talk in the test since the early 2000s
that the US and China need to you know
since China is emerging as a major
power. Um the US and China need to be
the two poles in the emerging world
order. China became very significant you
could say 2008 2007 2008 onwards after
the global financial crisis in which
China did a lot to actually stabilize
the US dollar for their own reasons
obviously um
and after 2012 once Mr. region being
came to power the China you could see a
very different China going forward and
China obviously is a very major economy
now the second largest economy and uh
technologically very advanced or maybe
in some areas potentially even a
significant challenger rival maybe even
more advanced than the US in some
specific areas
um so the G2 so the so the US wants a
bipolar world order and China will also
be very happy with a bipolar world order
in which it it controls half of the
world right Neither the US nor China
wants a multipolar world order which is
messy. They don't want a third pole of
India, Russia and the global south or
maybe four poles like Russia as a poll
of its own with its own set of nations
which cooperates with China as well as
India and the global south. No one wants
that sort of mess. So the US and China
both seek a G2 situation, a cold war
situation where the rivalry
can be managed. See, in the in the 20th
century, the US and the USSR were major
adversaries with massive amounts of
nuclear weapons pointed at each other,
but they also cooperated in a variety of
ways to manage the relationship and keep
the tensions from spilling over beyond
what anyone wanted. Right? So the so
that's what the US and China wants. And
now the US seems to have resigned itself
to the fact that China is now well
almost a peer equal to the US. China
doesn't have any of the advantages in
the power projection domain that the US
has very similar to the situation of the
USSR. Right? So China faces all those
all those problems all those issues all
those drawbacks. But China is is bound
it's hamstrung by these issues by the
chi by the by the island chains and so
much more. But China has some advantages
that the USSR did not have technological
advancement and and uh a far better
system of governance than the USSR. And
so it's it's a different situation but a
similar situation. So the US it seems to
have now decided that it's going to
withdraw into the western hemisphere and
it's going to defend the western
hemisphere from Chinese encroachments
and it kind of is giving away the
eastern hemisphere to some extent to
China. It still wants to have as much
you know that it's not giving up its
power projection capabilities in the
eastern hemisphere. It's not giving up
its occupation of Japan or South Korea.
It's not g giving up its u possession
you could say of Australia of all the
assets it has cultivated and and
you know created in Southeast Asia. It
is not giving up east or west Pakistan.
It also seeks to expand its footprint
through Bagram air base. It seeks that
it seeks to pressurize and contain
India. Maybe even turn India into so
it's not giving up any of that. But it's
it's the US is now clear that China is
the dominant power in the eastern
hemisphere despite all of this.
So it's going to contain China. It's
going to contain India. It's going to
try and pressurize India into becoming a
vasal. If India refuses, it will try and
do a regime change in India. All of that
is going on. And if India somehow
refuses and succeeds in not becoming a
vasal of the US, does it mean that India
will have to become a Chinese vasal?
That also well if Mr. Modi stays in
power and if when whenever he steps down
at whatever point in time maybe 5 10
years whatever it is and if there is
continuity in the political and
geopolitical policy of the U of India
then India will find itself in a strange
situation with China also China will
want India to be a vasal and just like
we are saying no to the US we'll say no
to China also so we could face a lot of
pressure from multiple fronts we could
face instability we could wars, we could
face proxy wars, resumption of proxy
wars, east, west, whatever, all of that.
So, like I said, we are entering a
period of significant geopolitical
instability.
As the world order rearranges itself,
there's going to be a lot of
instability. It's like an earthquake
happening. You know, global tectonic
plates are changing and shifting and
that causes earthquakes. It's like that.
So India has the choice of either
becoming a US vasal or going into RAIC
as as a junior partner of China or
staying completely sovereign which is
the ideal situation but it is um a
course of action that that will be
difficult next 20 years will be
difficult ideally that's what happens uh
and and we then emerge as a major
economy in 15 20 years and then it will
be very hard for others to bully us but
that's going to take a lot of fortitude
and a lot of hard choices and lot of
insignificant amounts of various kinds
of pain. That's where we are.
Rushab says, "Why is the US threatening
Venezuela with an attack? Is it just
because of Maduro or oil game through
which the US wants more control over
global energy or any other plans to
dominate South America?" Mlevin says,
"Vene Venezuela's President Maduro has
asked Russia for urgent military support
and there are reports of Russian arms
appearing in Venezuela.
This seems exactly like the Cuban
missile crisis." Guess the history does
repeat itself.
Okay, so in the 20th century, we had a
nation in the Western Hemisphere in the
Caribbean region. There was Cuba that
was aligned with the USSR. and Cuba. If
you look at the map, we haven't opened
the map today. Let's do that now. Where
is map? We open map. Give me a second
and we shall visit Cuba through the map.
Okay. Where is map? We put on screen.
Right here we are. So, if we look at
Cuba, you will see it's right at, you
know, in in the US's backyard, Gulf of
Mexico, which is now the Gulf of
America, that sort of thing, right?
So, here is Cuba. this large island
nation right in the US's backyard and it
remained sovereign. it did not bend into
the you know cave into the US and a
whole truckload of sanctions were
applied on Cuba and as a result Cuba its
economy froze and it still you know if
you visit Cuba it will feel like you've
stepped into the 1950s
>> that's how it feels but Cuba remained
independent with the help of the USSR
and it still has remained more or less
sovereign nation even though now you
know it's open to US tourists and
whatnot so it's now a little different
when it comes to Venezuela
So what happened in the 1960s, the Cuban
missile crisis, 1962
is that the USSR had placed
ballistic missiles with nuclear warheads
in Cuba. That was seen as the as a
direct threat by the US and you know an
immediate threat right in in their
backyard. So uh when the US places
nuclear weapons in various countries
like for example Turkey and so on, they
say that the Russians should not see it
as a direct threat while they saw
Russian missiles and warheads in Cuba as
as you know an immediate threat that
they that almost led to nuclear war.
So that's the Cuban missile crisis
issue. Now is Venezuela the situation
right now similar to the Cuban missile
crisis? It is not because there are no
Russian ballistic missiles or nuclear
warheads in Venezuela as of today as far
as we know. Okay. So, first of all, we
have to understand that it's not exactly
the same thing. And Russia today is not
as powerful as the USSR used to be
comparatively to the US in the 1960s or
in the 20th century during the cold war.
So then the question is why is the US
threatening Venezuela with attack and
why is Venezuela urgently asking for
urgent military support from Russia?
What's the deal? See Venezuela Mr.
Maduro
he sees himself as a socialist. He sees
himself uh
as as someone who opposes US hedgemony.
So the US historically for the longest
time since the 19th century has had
something called the Monroe Doctrine
which is a term that's supposedly
obsolete today but it's still very much
enforced. The Monro Doctrine says that
nobody will be allowed no nation apart
from the US will be allowed to play any
colonial games in the Americas whether
it's North America, South America.
Essentially it means that the US will be
the overlord of all the nations in this
region whether it's Canada whether it is
Mexico whether it's the central a
central American nations like Panama etc
or the Latin American nations like
Brazil Argentina Cuba Chile and so on
Honduras
Uruguay
etc. But Venezuela is right there and
Venezuela is not aligned with the US.
Venezuela is aligned with the global
south and with Russia and uh as such the
US doesn't get to decide Venezuela's
economic policy its foreign policy and
so on. The way the US very strongly
let's say influences the economic and
foreign policies of the other nations in
the region. It's not the case with
Venezuela. So Venezuela is sovereign
to a large extent from the US. Right.
um not 100% sovereign but significantly
more sovereign than the other nations in
the region in Venezuela. Why is it
important? Because it has these huge
reserves of oil that makes it an
extremely important nation. So the US
would like to change the situation. They
would like Venezuela to become just like
any other South American nation or any
nation in the Americas and
be aligned completely with the US. And
the US should decide
or or or guide this nation about what
kind of economic and foreign policy it
should have essentially a vasal state.
That's what they would like Venezuela to
be. And since Venezuela has resisted
this for such a long time, the Americans
have imposed all kinds of sanctions on
Venezuela which has really crippled the
Venezuelan economy. And then you blame
it on socialism that you are so poor and
you have such terrible circumstances
because of socialism when it when
actually when in reality it's because of
the sanctions. So now maybe the US wants
to like like I said they have decided to
play defense in the western hemisphere
and they will kind of allow China to
dominate to some extent the eastern
hemisphere. So if the US wants to play
defense in the western hemisphere they
have to control the whole of the western
hemisphere. They control all the western
European nations. We understand that
very well through NATO through the EU
and so on. But they don't control
Venezuela. And Brazil also is an issue
but we'll not talk about Brazil right
now. Brazil is an issue to some extent.
So what do you do with Venezuela? You
affect the regime change. You first give
the Nobel Prize, peace prize to a lady
who you have cultivated and who would
you who you would like to be the next
leader in Venezuela just like Muhammad
Yinus, a former Nobel Prize winner is
now the the face of the Bangladeshi
military regime. Similarly, they would
like this lady, I don't know remember
her name, they would like her to be the
face of a new puppet government in
Venezuela.
That is the situation, right? So, it
looks like the US may potentially
sometime soon perhaps invade Venezuela.
Yeah, there are there is enhanced there
is augmented US naval activity in the
region. Maybe the US is preparing for an
invasion of Venezuela. And Venezuela's
terrain is is kind of challenging and
all, but the US can, I'm sure, over
time, deal with it, unless Venezuela
is able to defend itself properly, for
which it will need significant supplies
of arms, ammunitions, you know, military
systems and so on. And that's why the
Venezuelan government, Mr. Madur's
government have requested Russia for
urgent military support. and maybe
perhaps Russian arms are appearing in
Venezuela. So it's not exactly like the
Cuban missile crisis, but it's kind of
similar to it in in in a in various
ways. So why does the US want Venezuela?
First of all, to align the whole of the
Western hemisphere with the US and
secondly obviously oil very important.
If you take Venezuela, you get to
control the way the oil is sold, to whom
it's sold, to whom it's not sold, what
price and so on. So that way you can
control more of the global oil supply
which is obviously very welcome if if
you're the US. So that in a nutshell is
what is happening. What will happen?
Can't say. Hopefully, there is no
warfare and and such because it'll be
disastrous for an already uh devastated
country, a country that's devastated by
sanctions. But let's see. The US is
fully capable of taking Venezuela over
and uh affecting a regime change. That's
that's fully the US is definitely
capable of that. Very much so. Unless
the Russians get involved and uh bolster
the defensive capabilities of the nation
in which case the US may perhaps
reconsider if Russia is able to supply
sufficient arms, ammunition and whatnot
to Venezuela. That's where we are.
Sur
Sharma says finally we are making a
civilian aircraft.
There's a deal between H and a Rashin
company. What are my views about this?
Okay, we are talking about the Sukoy
Super Jet 100. What does this aircraft
look like? So, it's an aircraft that
that that it's a reasonably smallish
aircraft. It can accommodate about 100
105 passengers. It's a passenger jet.
What does it look like? Let's quickly
take a look at that. Let's go to our
friend Google and Google the Sukoy
Superjet 100. Sukoy Superjet 100. What's
it look like?
Um, so this is what it looks like. It's
a narrowbody aircraft.
Passengers about about a 100ish I would
say. Um, and it is a twin jet aircraft.
And that's the deal. So now now that we
know what this aircraft looks like,
what's this deal that we have between
India and Russia, between H and this
Russian company? I forget the name of
the company. You can look it up. The
deal is that India will manufacture
between 75 to 100 of these aircraft in
India.
Now what kind of manufacturing is the
question? What kind of manufacturing?
Are we going to import kits and assemble
those in India with screwdrivers?
Not quite. We're going to actually
manufacture the aircraft in India. We're
going to manu various Yeah. So various
components and and parts of the aircraft
like the like the like the body of the
aircraft, various uh systems of the
aircraft, all of these will be locally
manufactured in India. So we essentially
manufacturing the majority of the
aircraft in India itself. We'll procure
the raw materials and create and
manufacturing everything inhouse with a
license from Russia. So licensed
production but the jet engines won't be
manufactured in India. Those will come
from Russia and these are Russian. It's
it's an advanced version of the previous
jet engine they were using. So what this
will do is that it will give us an
aircraft that has nothing that's
manufactured in the west or coming from
the west.
>> So in the in the case of the west in the
future you know imposing restrictions,
sanctions whatever on India we're going
to be able to have these aircraft that
are non-western. So for example if you
are using boeings or airbuses or
whatever if the US decides they can stop
supplying spare parts for
[clears throat] servicing and whatn not
to India in that case we have to ground
our fleets right see Airbus is a French
company but the US can arm twist the
French we know that very well even
though France is the only nation in the
EU and and NATO that is way more
sovereign than the others a quasa
independent foreign policy and whatnot
but still so if we manufacture this
entirely nonwestern
passenger aircraft in India. It's great
for us, right? So, it will be what what
is the range that it has? It's it's a
range of about 3 3 to 4,000 maybe 4,500
kilometers, right? So, that's that's
good enough for India domestic uh air
air traffic, right? Uh various uh second
tier, third tier airports that we wish
to connect through the udan scheme, etc.
we'll be able to to cover these with
these Sukoy super jads. So it's so so
it's fantastic. It's I think the first
time we will be manufacturing an an
aircraft entirely almost entirely in
India after many decades. So overall
it's fantastic and uh that will give us
a lot of technological knowhow and maybe
in the future we can modify augment the
aircraft maybe with Russian permission
license whatever and produce a new
family of aircraft based on this one
maybe more maybe larger aircraft with
with higher capacity whatever so I would
say it is uh it's fantastic I'm glad to
see that this is happening finally right
uh it's a very positive development for
us it's great for India Russia
relations. It's great for India's
atmandera campaign. It's great for
Indian manufacturing. It's great for
India's commercial uh air sector and so
much more. Overall, it's a fantastic
deal. And the great thing is that we're
not we're not assembling kits in India.
We're going to be manufacturing the
aircraft almost entirely in India. Apart
from the engines and about the engines,
maybe we can see about that also. What
to do? Maybe we can eventually even
manufacture the engines in India, which
is not part of the current deal. But you
know, even that could happen in the
future. the the the doors are of the
doors of possibility are always open. So
I see this as a fantastic uh development
overall.
Okay, we have to discuss this don't we?
Real painter says will mamani kiss the
ring. Real painter again says zoramqami
mandani has won the New York City
mayoral elections by okay 50% preference
vote. Okay, I've not seen the the margin
of victory but he has won. Okay, good.
And he has also quoted the magnificent
Shir Shri Mr. Nehuji in his winning
speech and Hindutwa Rises says is
Zaharan Mani becoming mayor going to
affect India US relations or will Zuran
be subordinate to Trump? I don't think
Trump is a big fan of socialism and
doesn't want it to exist in the US.
What is the deal? So, Zoran Mandani has
won the New York City mayoral elections
and the Indian media is right now going
gaga. Indian origin Zoran Mandani has
won. Haha, great, wonderful, fantastic.
So, in what way is Indian origin? His
his mother is Miranayar.
She is a Punjabi. She's a very famous
world famous uh filmmaker, film
director, right? Miranar and his father
is also Indian origin. He's an Indian
origin Muslim. I think Gujarati speaking
Muslim who was born in Mumbai but he was
in Uganda or something and he moved to
the US in probably in the 1970s or
something like that. So both his parents
are of Indian origin and that obviously
makes Zhan Mandani an Indian origin
American. Now he has won the New York
mayoral elections. He is a far-left c
far-left guy. His ideology is is leftist
ideology
and uh when he in his victory speech he
apparently quoted the great magnificent
Sri Javahar Lan Neuji and that has
pleased a lot of Indians right um
right so the question is first question
is will Mamani kiss the ring what do we
mean by kiss the ring so kiss the ring
is this analogy I had used
sometime last here late last year during
the US presidential campaign in which I
had said that if Trump wins the
presidency of the US
then it will mean that he has kissed the
ring of the deep state. Kissing the ring
means expressing or promising your
allegiance to someone to someone
powerful and dangerous. It comes from
the movie The Godfather. If you watch
that you will see this scene of the
Godfather extending his ring out there.
Here you go. And the supplicant has to
go down on his knees and kiss the ring.
Which means that I am your man now. I'm
yours.
I'm yours to command. So that's what we
mean by kissing the ring. Now whose
ring? Essentially it means the deep
state's ring. So the question is will
Mamani kiss the ring? Mamani doesn't
have to kiss the ring. He has already
kissed the ring. Mamani is a candidate
that's aligned with the objectives and
agendas of the of whoever runs the west.
the west overall.
>> Okay. So, let's first discuss this. What
is the deal? How come this guy has won?
A guy with no prior experience in in
administering a city or or a village or
anything. A guy with no experience,
no governance experience of any kind,
but he has won. How did he win? Are the
people of New York really convinced that
he this guy with no experience is going
to do a great great job in running New
York City? what's happening and why is
it that we are seeing this this rise of
various uh Indian origin Muslim
candidates v you know mayors for example
you we have the mayor of London Sadi
Khan who's also of Indian origin okay
some people will say he's of Pakistani
origin but before 1947 there was no
Pakistan right so he's obviously of
Indian origin
um what is happening
what's going on there is this rise of
various Muslim people who take who are
either becoming prime ministers
or or they are becoming mayors in
various parts of the UK also in the US.
So see the US the US conservatives have
this huge problem with Hindus but they
are okay with and and they will oppose
any any Hindu person tooth and nail like
Vive Ramaswami is being opposed like
Usha Vance is being uh dragged through
the coals for for remaining Hindu and
not converting to Christianity. You will
have all of that but you will never see
this happening to Indian Muslims. Why is
that?
So there seems to be look my views about
this are still evolving
but there seems to be
see whoever is running the west whoever
is actually running and ruling the west
they seem to have decided that we're
going to introduce Islam in a big way in
the western world
because Christianity is now a dying
religion in the west at least in India
etc it's being introduced on an indust
real scale through conversion activities
and what not right but in the western
world Christianity is dying in Europe
people are leaving Christianity
Christianity in droves when the pope
comes to some country no one even turns
up to see him Christianity is is is
losing it its foothold in the west and
the US also lots of people have moved
away from Christianity so the west seems
to have decided that you know if we
don't have the sort of religion that can
control the people like Christianity
used to do. We have to introduce
something else that will do the same
thing. Historically, Christianity was a
religion of of strict control.
You know, if you went against the
tenants of Christianity, you would be
burned at the at the stake. You would be
declared a heretic and all kinds of
things nasty things would happen to you
to you and your family. So, people were
rigidly controlled through Christianity
even after the the the rise of protest
protestantism and and whatnot.
But now, it's not the case. You can
leave Christianity and nothing happens
to you. There's no consequences. But not
the case with Islam. So the Abrahamic
religions are are are political
religions. It's one of the great
strengths of Islam that it's a political
religion. It's not a criticism. It's a
strength. Okay? And
and Islam can be used to replace
Christianity to to control the people.
So that's why you are seeing that Islam
is being introduced in a big way in the
west. there is this uh engineered
immigration of people from certain parts
of the world in a big way in various
western countries and u we are seeing
this happening and maybe they want Islam
to become an integral part of the west
so that they can keep controlling the
people through this religion because
Christianity is no longer that useful or
viable anymore and so we also have the
other religion which is which used to be
called wokeism or whatever But that's
also kind of a religion, you know, with
its own uh ideology and whatnot. So,
this is a long-term game.
It's not something that they want to use
to control their flock for the next 5,
10 years. It's about how to control the
world for the next 100, 200 years.
That's the game. And that's why people
like Zoharam Mandani emerge from nowhere
and
succeed in becoming, you know,
in in in winning things like the New
York election, mayoral election. We have
Sadi Khan winning mayor mayorship of
mayorhood whatever you call it of of
London repeatedly and so on. So uh Zoran
Mandani is already in line with the
agenda. He doesn't have to kiss any
ring. He's already kissed the ring the
essentially the the day a long time ago.
So is Zoran Mandani becoming mayor going
to affect India's US relations? Will he
be subordinate to Trump? He is not going
to be subordinate subordinate to Trump.
He's going to be in opposition to Trump.
But understand this opposition is all
stage managed. The US has what the the
left and the right. The rep the
Democrats are the left, Republicans on
the right. So Zan is left. I'm not sure
if he's a Democrat or not, but he's
left. So he's on that on that side. But
whether you are a Democrat or a
Republican, whether you are left or
right,
if you come to power in the US, you
serve the same agenda. You have the same
foreign policy, same military policy,
same all of that. So at the end of the
day, both left and right serve the
overall agenda of whoever is ruling the
west. You can call it the deep state or
whatever. So domestically in the US,
Zoharan, Mahani and Trump will be polls
apart. They will oppose each other.
Trump will criticize Mamani. Mamani will
criticize Trump. They will mock and tone
each other. That's fine.
But
that's that's how it is. So So Zoran
becoming mayor, will it affect India US
relations? Not
to a very large extent. Um but he is an
anti-India person by the way. He will
speak Hindi very well because it's not
his mother tongue. His mother tongue is
tongue is Punjabi. If you speak Punjabi,
you will obviously speak Hindi. He also
speaks Arabic. I suppose he may speak
his father's language also. Whatever.
He seems to be very Indian and all, but
overall he's anti-India.
You
may not believe that perhaps some of you
at this point in time, but he is going
to be very anti-India.
So it's it may not have any effect on
the India US relations because he's not
the president. He's just the mayor of a
city but the world's greatest city like
many people consider New York to be. So
it's not a small position even if he's
just just a mayor. He's the mayor of the
US's financial capital and the world's
financial capital. So that is definitely
a very powerful very important position.
So he will not have
a good
impact or effect on India's US
relations. At best he will have no
effect. But most likely he will have
some kind of deledious effect on India
US relations and in what way it remains
to be seen. But I don't expect uh his
effect to be to be positive when it
comes to the India US relationship. At
best it will be neutral or most more
likely it will be in some way negative.
Very early days he won today. Let's wait
and watch but that's how I expect things
to unfold.
Right. Next question.
Nikita Vashish says, "The US has more
satellites than Russia, India, China
combined. What leverage does it give the
US? Does the US have too many of these
satellites? What's the use of all these
satellites? Also do a space special
someday." Okay. Rahul Gun says, "Does
the recent 5-tonon satellite launched by
ISRO's LVM 3 M5 rocket does it represent
a significant step forward for India or
is it still not such a big deal
according to me? Because I've been a
long-term proponent of ISRO not punching
high enough." Okay, let us uh address
these multiple questions. First of all,
does the US have too many such lines?
The US has as of now
more than 10,000
active satellites. More than 10,000
active satellites. Can you believe that
number? Can you imagine how many
satellites are out there? Right? More
than 10,000 active satellites. So what
does the US do with the satellites?
They have too many of these. Are the are
these pointless? These are not
pointless. These are very useful, very
important, right? And see the space
sector is the next step in in
exploration. And I have said this for
years. I have said this since 2021 that
the two or three nations that will lead
the world in the space race
in the 21st century are the two or three
nations that will decide the future of
humanity and the two or the nation that
will rule the world. So your position in
the space race is an indicator of how
much of whether you rule the world or
not eventually in the 21st century. So
these 10,000 plus satellites. What does
the US do with these? See, first of all,
many of these satellites are
communications satellites, global
communications, local communications.
They provide various services, internet
services, voice services, data services.
We need that. Yeah, satellites provide
those. So you have communication
satellites, you have navigation and
timing satellites, the GPS
constellation, the the American GPS, it
it globally is the backbone. It's the
foundation for navigation. Whether it is
civilian navigation, whether it is
commercial navigation, whether it's
military navigation also GPS is the
foundation of this. So you have a
constellation of GPS satellites. Then
you have intelligence satellites,
national security applications of
satellites, spy satellites, you know,
surveillance operations, reconnaissance
activities, encrypted secure
communications,
um then missile warning systems. Then
you have battle space coordination,
battlefield coord coordination, um
integration of various assets, military
assets together so that they all see the
same view of the battle space which is
provided by all the different assets
piece by piece. But the satellite puts
it all together with the help of
computers and then it gives every asset
a full view of the battle space, a full
integrated picture. That's very
important. Satellites do that. Then you
you have activities like earth
observation that can be regular earth
observation or very specific earth
observation which is spying activity you
know high resolution images in real time
of what's happening on the planet very
important but you also have things like
weather monitoring
you know scientific things like uh
scientific activities like monitoring of
of climate change over time uh
monitoring natural disasters
if they happen monitoring agricultural
developments and soil soil quality and
and whatnot right there is that then um
you have obviously a very large number
of Starlink satellites that is global
highspeed internet those satellites may
be dual purpose satellites they may also
have other purposes that are being
served there right so you have all these
all these benefits of having satellites
and and and every satellite is
different. A single satellite will not
give you all these benefits, right?
Every satellite will have a certain
function. So or a specific set of of of
functions that is assigned to it. Now if
you have all these satellites 10,000 of
of these satellites which do different
things, what benefit does it give you?
Right? So one thing if you have this
gigantic number of satellites and this
tremendous diversity of satellites they
all do so many different things. This
helps the United States maintain its
technological leadership in the world.
It ensures that there is continuous
development continuous innovation
in the US. They want better and better
satellites. Right? There is development
in the space launching technologies
reusable rockets. Say if you have so
many satellites and you need to keep on
replenishing those, you need lots and
lots of launches, space launches. So
that has given rise to the reusable
rocket technology that that space X has
developed. This for that you also need
to you know
better miniaturaturize satellites. So
that also is a technological
advancement.
Um so all of this ensures the
technological superiority of the US.
Then you have global influence. the US
um you know the US is able to because of
the gigantic number of satellites it's
able to control these this uh
infrastructure because it owns it and
this gives the US the power to influence
uh whatever happens in the world. It it
can influence uh the standards for space
technology. It it gives the US military
leverage. It gives the US leverage in
diplomacy, global diplomacy. It makes
the US the primary uh provider of of
security. It it gives the US uh
hedgemony and and primacy in all its
security alliances because all the other
partners will depend on US military and
other technology communications
technology. It also gives US primacy in
economic relationships and partnerships
with with with everybody. It positions
the US as the dominant partner in very
asymmetric relationships. Military uh
you know the US military is very deeply
integrated with all these space-based
assets. Uh it gets real time data, gets
realtime intelligence. The satellites
allow the US military to to
control and command assets all across
the world. The US has more than 700 extr
territorial military bases with the US
military uh assets deployed all across
the globe. How do you command how do you
control all of that cohesively? Right?
So these satellites they give the US the
ability for this uh to to command and
control all these assets cohesively.
um the US is able to do precision
targeting
of when whenever there's a military
operation if you need precision
targeting the satellites give it the
ability to do do that. So all of this
gives the US tremendous asymmetrical
advantages of over anybody or any
adversary.
Um now the US is the leading
commercial
um launcher of satellites and it also
has the largest number of commercial
satellites that have been deployed and
these serve so many markets globally
right so the US it's able to capture all
this economic value from the space
economy and this is projected to be
worth trillions of dollars in this
century
um and and so much more. So all of these
these satellites this this this massive
fleet of satellites, it gives the US a
tremendous advantage in all these
different sectors, communication,
navigation, military, defense, um
economic and commercial activities,
diplomacy, science, whatnot. Right? So
this strengthens the US national
security. It strengthens, it augments
the American economic power and it
enables the US to set global norms,
global rules in the space sector and it
obviously enables the US to maintain its
superiority in the global emerging
geopolitical competition for space. The
rush for the moon, everyone's rushing
back to the moon. Eventually, it's going
to be Mars. There's going to be space
tourism. There's going to be
militarization of space. There's going
to be eventually asteroid mining and so
much more. So all of this for all of
this you need to have a massive
satellite fleet, a massive space
industry. So all of this it it is
central to America's global leadership
uh not just in the past century but in
this coming century in the 21st century.
So space is going to increasingly be
central to geopolitical power and not
it's not just nations but corporations
within nations that are going to play a
pivotal role in all of this in in
securing access to space securing
perhaps territory outside of earth maybe
on the moon maybe in Mars uh in in
shaping the rules and the norms of how
to behave in space what you can do what
is allowed what is not allowed right?
They get to decide. We don't get to
decide. And all of this will protect us
um interests
beyond
our planet. Right? So, so hopefully this
explains why the US has invested so much
in the space sector. The US invests in
the future. They don't react. They set
the scene. They set they they formulate
the rules. They set the rules. and
everybody else marches to that beat and
they abide by the rules. So if you want
to be a leading power in the world, you
have to be re not reactive, you have to
be proactive. And the only nation beyond
the US that is being proactive is
currently China. Even Russia is is
tagging along with China. So that's the
deal. So considering what I have just
explained 10,000 plus satellites and all
everything that these satellites achieve
for the US and all the advantages these
satellites give to the US do you think
one five ton satellite launch is going
to put India in any kind of advantageous
position
is it that great
I'm not saying it's bad thing it is not
a bad thing I'm happy that ISRO has used
its most powerful rocket which is a
medium lift vehicle
to uh put this 5-tonon satellite into
orbit. Good. It's good to see a launch
by ISRO after a certain period of time.
The US launches weekly. The Chinese
launch so many times a year. I don't
know how many times ISRO launches per
year, five, six times. I'm not sure. I
may be wrong. Maybe 15 times, maybe
three times. I'm not sure. But it's
nothing comparable to to what the US is
doing. And our heaviest and most
powerful rocket is a medium lift rocket.
Okay, please be cognizant of this fact.
I'm not sure when we're going to develop
reusable rocket technology. Probably by
the 2030s when it's already old
technology because SpaceX developed the
technology like 15 years ago.
So I do not see India being currently
even a player in the space race and I
don't blame ISRO for this. ISRO is
fantastic. ISRO with these tiny limited
budgets achieves so much
right
engineers are brilliant. ISRO's ISRO is
a fantastic organization. It's one of
the one of the organizations that shows
India what we are capable of.
But it needs the budget. It needs the
the the projects, right? It needs the
right kind of leadership, the right kind
of ambition that has to come from
outside of ISRO
because ISRO does what it's told right
by the government of India. So that's
the problem. I don't see India I it's
not about ISRO not punching high enough.
It's about India not having the ambition
of being a leading space power. We just
okay we are there in space. We have
ISRO. We can launch satellites. We don't
depend on others to launch satellites
except very large ones in which case we
will either go to France or to SpaceX
but otherwise we can launch satellites
and maybe in 5 10 years we will have a
rocket that is twice as powerful as the
one we have and maybe in 10 15 years
we'll have perhaps reusable rockets. So
we are this this is the standard Indian
way of doing things
develop technologies that others have
developed 20 30 years ago now that's
what we keep doing and that is what
obviously frustrates me because we are
capable of so much more. We're capable
of leading the world in space but
whoever is in charge
maybe doesn't see sufficient value right
now in us doing that. See,
see the Chinese
the Chinese always plan ahead. The
Chinese see themselves as a superpower
even though they currently are not. And
even 20 years ago, they were seeing
themselves as a superpower. And they
were putting the the the the pieces in
place
that would
ensure that when China becomes maybe
three times more powerful, it will have
all the capabilities already in place.
Not that once we reach a 20 trillion
dollar economy, then we will start
developing X kind of rocket or Y kind of
rocket. No, they started doing that when
they were a $3 trillion economy. So
China always seeks to punch way ahead of
its of its weight and India waits until
it reaches a certain weight category to
start behaving like that that weight
category. That's the difference between
India and China and that is obviously
going to be a source of frustration for
people who understand what's happening
and what we are capable of. All right
next
says why does India only have nine
military satellites? The US has 250
plus. China and Russia have 150 plus.
The US has about 250ish military
satellites. Russia has about 100 110 or
so. China has more than 150 150 160
something like that. India well we don't
exactly know how many of India's
satellites that we have launched are
military satellites but most likely
maybe 15 20 are either military
satellites or dual use satellites that
can be used for civilian as well as
military purposes. Why is that the case?
Why does India have so few military
satellites?
Right? Because India focuses on the
subcontinent and slightly beyond the
subcontinent. India doesn't seek to know
everything that's happening across the
world. India is only focused on its
local region. We are not an ambitious
country. And you know the Chinese, they
have a global GPS- like constellation.
They started putting it up like 15 20
years ago when Okay, let's Google this.
Let's let's try and fact check this uh
Chinese GPS uh name. What is it called?
BU BU GPS BU BDS. Okay, BU BDS. Uh what
is it? What? Okay, it has been fully
operational since 2020.
And uh when did they start developing
this? When did China start developing
China start developing
what's it say
in 1994
three-stage process first phase
providing services within China second
stage Asia Pacific by 2012 third stage
global services by 2020 now what is the
Indian GPS like Indian GPS
uh Navik Navic is an indigenous thing it
extends 1500 km beyond its border ers
and I'm not sure what future plans we
have. So as you can see our ambitions
are very modest.
We seek to be 1500 km beyond our borders
and beyond that we have no idea for that
we will develop will depend on other
countries. Uh so that's the deal. So why
does India? So my point is we are
talking about Navik, we're talking about
BU but it it shows you the extent of a
nation's ambition.
So when we talk about something like BU
or Navik or even GPS that's dual use
technology that has civilian
applications it also has very military
specific applications and our military
area of influence or or area of interest
rather is the subcontinent and 1500 km
beyond India's borders nothing more so
our ambition at best right now based on
these actions not on words see forget
the words. Forget the words. Forget
about what so and so leader has said in
words. Look at the actions. Our actions
are very modest.
So why? Because our ambitions are
limited. That's why.
So Ari says you have been vocal that
Indian Navy should focus on submarines
not on aircraft carriers. Why?
Why Abijit do you keep on saying this?
Why do you keep saying Abijit that India
should focus on submarines not on
aircraft carriers?
Why is it so? Aircraft carriers are very
difficult to sink. It's very difficult
to sink the carrier as the mechanical
structure is such and it is guarded by a
carrier group unlike submarines. Why?
It's a good question. It's it's an
excellent question and maybe I should
explain in detail.
Right. So what's the deal with aircraft
carriers? Are they obsolete or are they
still relevant?
They are not entirely obsolete but the
use the the use cases for aircraft
carriers are shrinking
and the threats are increasing.
Some nations can afford to put a big
ring around their aircraft carrier. A
proper aircraft carrier strike group
with like 20 destroyers and other assets
that create concentric defensive rings
around aircraft carriers. Imagine how
expensive that is. Now, why do I said
there is increasing
set of there's an increasing set of
threats for aircraft carriers which is
printing the use cases. Why is that so?
So, let's first examine the threats that
we have. There are now extremely
advanced anti-hship missiles.
Secondly, there are hypersonic weapons,
very dangerous hypersonic weapons. There
are now more and more sophisticated
submarines and then we have the advent
of unmanned systems of various kinds.
These things have fundamentally altered
what you call the risk calculus that
aircraft carriers face. Okay. So let's
go into detail. I spoke about anti-hship
missiles, advanced anti-hship missiles.
One is
the anti-ship ballistic missiles. So,
China is has been developing for quite
some time these so-called carrier killer
missiles. Okay, there is DF21D
and there is the DF26B.
These are two carrier killer missiles.
One has a shorter range 1500 or so km.
the the other one 26B has a range in
probably probably in excess of 4,000
kilometers. So these carrier killer
missiles, they're are ballistic missiles
and they can hone in on on a carrier
based on data that comes from satellites
like we discussed and they can
obliterate an aircraft carrier. They can
carry conventional warheads or even the
naughty ones, nuclear warheads. And it's
very difficult to to to
uh defend a carrier against that sort of
ballistic missile threat right and
because of this even look you may be
able to take down perhaps one two of
these but what if someone launches a
barrage like 10 of these at you it's
almost impossible to defend the aircraft
carrier strike group against that. So
because of this aircraft carriers then
have to operate thousands of kilometers
offshore away from contested regions to
remain beyond the range of such
missiles. And this significantly reduces
the combat reg combat radius of not just
the aircraft carrier not just the
aircraft aircraft carrier strike group
but also the aircraft that the aircraft
carrier carries. And that's the whole
purpose of an aircraft carrier to take
aircraft far beyond the shores of the
host country. Right? So that is those
carrier killer missiles. Then you have
hypersonic missiles. There are that are
what is the definition of hypersonic?
A missile that that travels faster than
mark 5 faster than five times the speed
of sound is a hypersonic missile. You
have the Russian Circon missile which is
faster which which flies faster than
Mark 8. Imagine that. Then the Russians
have something called the Avanguard
hypersonic glide vehicle. Mach 27.
How on earth do you defend yourself
against the MAC 27 weapon? 27 times the
speed of sound.
Even if you know how to defend, do you
understand how much it compresses your
decision-m timeline from the time you
detect something to what decision you
should take until and how much time you
have before it impacts you? It really
compresses that. So the faster a missile
is, the less lesser time you have to
make decisions and defend yourself and
perhaps save the aircraft carrier. Then
you have submarine threats. We did not
discuss that. Submarine threats. Now
here's an interesting event that
happened 20 years ago, 2005.
The Swedish have this submarine which is
called the Gautland class submarine. It
is a very cheap and small submarine. It
costs about $100 million which is super
cheap for submarines.
In 2005 there were these exercises off
the coast of California. Okay, Pacific
coast of the US. And in these exercises
a Swedish Gautland class submarine
repeatedly
sank the USS Ronald Reagan, a massive
super carrier of the US aircraft
carrier. So this one submarine the the
Gautland class submarine it was up
against an entire aircraft carrier
strike group. It had destroyers, it had
helicopters, it had anti-ubmarine
aircraft, right? And this submarine it
had air independent propulsion and it is
it operates extremely silently and it
was able to penetrate the aircraft
carrier strike groups defenses
multi-layered defenses and it was able
to score multiple stimulated torpedo
hits on the aircraft carrier. Right now
imagine if you the torpedo could be of
various kinds. The Russians have these
super cavitating
uh supersonic torpedoes. A torpedo can
carry regular warheads. It can also
carry the nasty ones, nuclear ones.
Right? If you're able to penetrate this
the defenses and you launch a torpedo,
you can blow the the aircraft carrier
out of the water.
So this submarine, it costs $100
million. The super carrier costs between
6 to 10, maybe 12 billion. Add to that
the cost of the strike group, the
protective cocoon, that's tens of
billions of dollars. So do you see uh
the cost benefit disparity over here,
right? Then you have things like drone
swarms, aerial UAVs that you can you can
use to swarm the the aircraft carrier.
You can even use underwater vehicles. So
this is of emerging threat, asymmetric
threat. And through this, you don't want
to destroy the aircraft car, you want to
disable it. You want to first of all
overwhelm the carrier defenses through
saturation attacks. Just numbers, sheer
numbers. It's it's just a mathematical
thing. If you have sufficient numbers,
you will overwhelm the defenses of the
strike group. And then you will you
don't have to sink the carrier. You have
to damage it. You have to damage the
flight deck deck. For example, during
operation Synindor, we cratered the the
the runways of Pakistani air bases. If
you if you put gaping holes in the
runways, the Pakistani fighter planes
can't take off or land. Similarly, if
you damage the flight deck of an
aircraft carrier, it is disabled. You
can't either take off or land from it.
So, it becomes completely ineffective.
Combat ineffective. Right? So, so now
you hopefully understand the kind of
threats that aircraft carriers face that
they did not face 30 years ago in 1990.
Things have changed significantly 35
years ago. Okay. And these threats are
even more pronounced in geographically
constrained waters. Choke points. We
have discussed choke points, haven't we?
The Mala straight, the straight of
Hormuz, the Red Sea, the Taiwan
straight. These are geographically
constrained waters, which means choke
points over there. This threat is
particularly pronounced. And aircraft
carriers are essentially sitting ducks,
especially against saturation attacks.
They will not survive that.
So aircraft carriers will now have to
stay away from these things. But
understand that the operational context
matters. So where do aircraft carriers
still remain effective? What are the use
cases we can think of? Huh? First of
all, aircraft carriers are effective um
when they are carrying out an operation
of power projection against what we call
non-per adversaries. So non-tier
adversaries means nations that are not
comparable in power or capabilities to
the to the to the host nation. So if I
am the US and I have the super advanced
powerful aircraft carrier and I am going
out there to bully let's say let's say
Somalia, Somalia is not a peer
adversary. So over there it's effective.
Somalia doesn't pose a threat to the US
or let's say they want to bully North
Korea. Well, North Korea they have to be
careful because North Korea has certain
weapons they don't they don't want to
face. So once again even versus North
Korea the US will have to keep the
aircraft carrier away from it reasonably
at a reasonable distance from the North
Korean uh assets. You see so aircraft
carriers are effective in uncontested or
lightly contested environments
where you where they where they up
against nonper adversaries. Okay. So
they are effective for power projection
and bullying against non-per
adversaries. They are aircraft carriers
are good for deterrence and diplomatic
signaling. Aircraft career is one lakh
tons of naval diplomacy gunboat
diplomacy just to show off your strength
and might and all that. Um they have the
symbolic pre symbolic u value you know
um they are symbols of national resolve
national prestige national capability
and uh they they're symbolic
assets in that in that sense and they
are good for patrolling uh you know
trade routes sea lanes of communication
um they're good for you know doing
patrolling jobs and sea sea control and
all of that and They are good for
bluewater operations, open water
operations in environments that are far
away from your adversary adversary and
your adversaries
the range of their missiles and from
their shores. So that is what aircraft
carriers are good for. If they enter a
contested environment, no matter how
many defenses you have, if the opponent
is capable, they will wipe your aircraft
carrier out of existence.
Now when it comes to India,
what do we seek to do? Who are our major
adversaries? What are our major threats?
One is East Pakistan, one is West
Pakistan. Do we need an aircraft carrier
for that? We don't.
Another one is China.
Do we want to send an aircraft carrier
into waters near China and bully China?
We don't seek to bully anybody.
We may face perhaps in the future a
Chinese aircraft carrier uh group coming
into the Bay of Bengal or something. So
what do you do? You do you face off with
that with an aircraft carrier? No, you
create A2A bubbles, anti-access area
denial bubbles through missiles and
other frightening things. You don't need
an aircraft carrier to counter an
aircraft carrier strike group. You
counter it asymmetrically.
But I'm not saying that we should wind
up our aircraft career program. It's a
hard one hardearned set of capabilities
and skills. So we should continue the
aircraft carriers that we already have.
But right now at this point in time
until we become a 20 trillion economy,
we should not invest in more of these.
That's my point. We should invest in
submarines. Submarines are stealthy,
invisible. They can go into your
contested spaces. They can go into your
choke points. they can go into your
constrained geop geographical
environments and and wreak mayhem there.
That's why submarines are more valuable
in today's environment
and technological set of circumstances
than the aircraft carrier. I hope I have
given a reasonably detailed explanation
of why I insist that India should invest
in submarines, various kinds of very
dangerous, deadly capable submarines
rather than more aircraft carriers. Keep
the aircraft carriers that we have. Keep
operating those but don't invest in
more. invest, use that money to build
more submarines, better submarines,
various kinds of submarines, diesel,
electric submarines, air independent
propulsion submarines, nuclear
submarines, ballistic missile
submarines, hunter killer submarines,
all of that.
Okay. Anonymous scientist says, "What
will happen to the global order if the
US achieves ASI?" What is ASI?
Archaeological Survey of India. Oh, it
means artificial super intelligence.
What do we mean by artificial super
intelligence? We hear the term AGI and
ASI thrown around all the time. What is
AGI? AGI is artificial general
intelligence and ASI is artificial super
intelligence. What's the difference?
AGI is an artificially intelligent
system that is capable of doing
essentially whatever human beings do. It
it essentially means that you have a
machine with an IQ of about 140 to 160,
a pretty intelligent human being who can
do everything a human being can do. All
the reasoning, all the thinking, all the
creativity, uh all the problem solving,
everything. So an AGI system is that
with an IQ of 140 to 160, ideally 150,
160, a very intelligent person. That's
what an AGI system is. Okay. What's an
ASI system? Well, think of it this way.
An artificially super intelligent system
will have all the capabilities of AGI,
but it's going to have an IQ of maybe
300, maybe 400, maybe 500. That's beyond
human capabilities. That if you achieve,
it will start giving you results that
are essentially science fiction results,
right?
It may well if you if you want to look
at non scary stuff it may be able to
give us a theory of quantum gravity it
may be able to reconcile general
relativity and quantum mechanics quantum
field theory that's what it may be able
to definitely do if it is an IQ of 300
or 500 it may be able to perhaps even
invent time travel travel technologies
maybe tell us how to create wormholes
traversible wormholes and whatnot that
sort of thing as that sort of things. So
the a nation
so that is just the scientific thing
that I'm talking about. It will it will
have all these military and defense and
intelligence and other applications.
And that means that the nation that has
invented ASI and controls ASI it it
possesses enormous immense amounts of
strategic advantages, economic
advantages, military advantages,
technological advantages. This will
usher in immediately a new era in
geopolitics where the balance is balance
in power is essentially radically
changed. So let's say the US like
anonymous scientist says let's say the
US achieves ASI what will happen the US
once it achieves ASI it will enjoy a
decisive military edge over everybody a
massive military edge over everyone
else. a massive intelligence edge over
everyone else. ASI will ensure that that
all the traditional forms of warfare and
defense become obsolete. The US will be
able to automate everything. It will be
able to automize automate all its
military offense and defense
capabilities. Right? It will able to it
will be able to optimize everything and
it will be able to outthink all of its
adversaries in real time right now as we
speak. And this will neutralize the
deterrence value of of military
equipment. It will neutralize the
deterrence value of nuclear arsenals. Uh
the US will be able to disrupt all the
infrastructure of its adversaries
through cybernetic cyber means. it will
be able to control all the narratives
via information warfare, information
dominance. U the US
it already dictates terms to the rest of
the world to a large extent. It will be
able to completely effectively dictate
terms to everybody including China,
Russia, everyone else. This will
completely reshape the the the nature of
the alliances and then the US will be
able to either
coers other nations into becoming its
basiles. It will offer partnership which
is vasal to everybody else or it will
ensure that any nation's resistance
becomes completely futile, completely
impractical and completely useless.
Right? And in a very short amount of
time you will have a tremendous
inequality growing inequality in
technological capability in influence in
power in wealth and because of this
resource competition will become
obsolete and there's going to be a
tremendous brain drain everybody will
seek to go to the US and in case this
ASI system
probably a military military ASI in case
This ASI is it's something that
self-improves
obviously an ASI will be a
self-improving system right so in case
it is a self-improving system and it is
strongly controlled hopefully by the US
uh then this gap in capabilities etc
will become un insurmountable
maybe for decades maybe for centuries
especially if the US guards the
technology aggressively and undermines
every other nation's efforts to develop
similar technology.
So if the US alone develops ASI, it's
game over for everybody else. If the US
and another nation, maybe China develop
ASI together, it will trigger a shocking
arms race and that could lead to results
we can't imagine, we can't foresee,
right? So both will try to undermine
each other and it will they will try to
align other nations with them and you're
going to have
a cold war perhaps on steroids
and uh then both nations may invest in
sabotage, espionage,
god knows what else to restrain each
other or to outdo each other. Um and
obviously there there's always the
threat that this ASI if it is you know
it will obviously be super intelligent
like a human with 300 IQ 500 IQ but if
it becomes somehow autonomous
if it is self-aware which ASI systems
most likely will be and if it somehow
manages to become autonomous because it
is it's a self-improving system then it
will immediately
guaranteed it will transcend the
national interest of the host nation
which created it and it will seek
broader control a broader scope of
control of the world and then we cannot
predict predict anything that happens
next maybe we are in the terminator
scenario then right so these are the
various things that could happen so ASI
will be a pivotal moment in human
history it will take humanity in a
direction where we have never gone
before and the consequences perhaps we
can't even imagine what those could be
but anyhow if we if we assume that that
the US it's able to first develop ASI
before anybody else and it's able to
properly control it and ensure it
doesn't run out of control then it's
going to be unchallengeable
right it's going to be unchallengeable
it will ensure that nobody else is able
to develop this technology and it's
going to be perhaps you know able to
rule for at least a century or two. So
it's unlike anything that's ever
happened before and maybe it could
happen soon maybe 5 10 years. Who knows
what kind of systems are being developed
in private in secret behind closed doors
like I've said so many times. So AI is
is is a gamecher and we are familiar
with AI. We have all these chat GPD like
systems out there which already are like
kind of magical. That's like talking to
a human being. But imagine what is being
developed behind closed doors and the
military applications of that. So
okay Aush Singh says do you don't you
think China was the biggest winner of
this entire Russia Ukraine thing? The
entire attention of the west went
towards Russia and Russia to an extent
became dependent on China for supply
chains is it gave China a leverage over
Russia. Please share your inputs. Okay.
Russia
um the Russia Ukan war. Most likely
China has been the biggest winner of
this. See now the US considers China to
be one of the G2, right? The US now has
officially stated that its doctrine is
going to be that of defending the
western hemisphere hemispheric defense
like it says.
So you the US seems to have now
officially conceded that China is like a
peer competitor
a G2 which means that they are kind of
implicitly saying that China is kind of
like them a superpower. I don't quite
agree because of the power projection
disparities but yes so China has
benefited a lot. Russia
whether you like it or not has kind of
become to some extent a junior partner
of China. Russia depends on China for so
many things. If China
stops purchasing Russian oil and and
other things then Russia will be in deep
trouble right. Uh so China has been who
are the other winners? So India it's
it's become more relevant geopolitically
ever since the uh Ukraine conflict
started. Um the US expected that they
would destroy Russia through sanctions
and whatnot and that has not happened.
Russia has actually become stronger
economically and militarily as well and
Russia doesn't isn't affected by
sanctions because it's an otarchy. So
the US so the US game plan hasn't
worked. So that has kind of to some
extent slightly diminished the US's
standing and prestige. Europe has has
has been a big uh it's been a big series
of setbacks for Europe ever since this
conflict began because US because the
the Europeans no longer are able to
purchase this this you know they no
longer have access to this uh
inexhaustible supply of cheap energy
that was flowing in from Russia through
Russian gas Nordstream and all that. So
Europe is de-industrializing. Germany
and other nations are are going
backwards economically. Bad days for
Europe. India, it's exposed India to all
kinds of problems. But India's relevance
has grown. No question. But overall, I
would say China has been the biggest U
beneficiary of this. It's now a G2
nation. In 2022, China was not regarded
as a G2 nation. Now the US president
himself has said that China is a G2
nation. So yeah, China has risen in
stature, in relevance
and uh not sure about power but in terms
of its sphere of influence and control
it's risen. So I would agree that China
has been the biggest winner of whatever
has happened in the Ukraine war thus far
overall macroscopic perspective.
Aayush says don't you don't you think
that Taiwan invasion by China is far
from reality? They know that they will
be immediately sanctioned and the US
might come to Taiwan's aid. What will
they achieve? A burnt and destroyed
island.
Look, honestly speaking, China doesn't
have to invade Taiwan. If they can keep
their ego aside, they don't have to
invade Taiwan.
they all they have to do is to continue
controlling the the airspace and naval
space around Taiwan and uh make further
inroads into Taiwan economically.
Excuse me. Taiwan is already to a
significant extent economically
integrated with China. A lot of
Taiwanese people work in China. A lot of
Chinese people were working in Taiwan.
I'm not sure what the situation right
now is uh but it's been that case,
right? A lot of the Taiwanese economy is
integrated with the Chinese economy.
Taiwan benefits from its economic um
ties with China. So all you have to do
is to make Taiwan completely integrated
with your economy and make Taiwan
dependent on you economically. You don't
have to set a foot in Taiwan. You don't
have to. The question is will that be
acceptable to the people of China who
regard Taiwan as a renegade province and
do they insist that we have to retake
proper full control of Taiwan with boots
on the ground. Will Xinping be able to
get away with not taking Taiwan
militarily and just continuing what is
continuing ideally see ideally it makes
no sense to invade Taiwan. Let the
situation continue for the next 20 30
years. Taiwan will become more and more
integrated with China and then that's
it. What else do you want? Right? You
you make it a Chinese appendage.
So um and what happens if China tries to
invade Taiwan? There's going to be war.
The US will come to Taiwan's aid in some
way or the other. Um in case Taiw in
case the Chinese military is very
superior and it's able to take Taiwan,
it will take it will be able to take it
island that's already been destroyed. It
won't take Taiwan intact.
everything that Taiwan has of value will
be destroyed by the time the Chinese
take it. That is a guarantee. So what's
the point? So I agree that that an
invasion of Taiwan doesn't really make
sense from a practical perspective. But
from a national pride and prestige
perspective, maybe it is important that
Xinping eventually
takes it. Yeah. So there are these
national pride considerations
that change the equations. Otherwise, it
doesn't really make a lot of sense to um
you know invade Taiwan militarily.
Aayush Singh says every n every major
nation except the US and Russia are
engaged in border conflicts except
Russia Ukraine thing but the US is alone
the dominant player in both the American
continent. How did the US manage to do
this except for a few nations? All are
under under US vasal. Doesn't this give
the US a huge leverage over any other
major global power or any other major
power in the globe? How did they achieve
this level of domination of dominance?
They achieved it step by step
incrementally over centuries. Even
before the US became a nation, the
process was already in place. It was
already in motion. So, we know it all
starts with Columbus discovering uh
the the Caribbean region, imagining that
he's in India, right? It all begins with
that. the Spaniards make the first
moves. Eventually by the 1600s the the
English start start entering the the
frey and between the 1600s early 1600s
all the way to the late 19th century
there are these endless American Indian
wars the European occupiers trying to
wipe out the natives right there is this
king Phillips war late 17th century
second half of the 17th century in which
there is there is major warfare then in
what 1775 5 to the 8 1780s there's the
American War of Independence in which
America becomes independent of England
but it still is a small geographical
areas if you want to see the map of the
US. Okay, let's see map of the US in
1783.
USA map 1783. Let's take a look at what
the US looked like in 1783.
You see this green portion?
Uh that's all it was. That's all it was.
So if you are a nation that occupies the
green portion that you see there, you
are not a major power. You are nowhere
close to being a major power. So what
does the US do? Right? So 1783 they win
the war of independence. They become so
they become independent of the of the
UK. In 1803
the Americans purchased Louisiana. the
Louisiana purchase from uh Napole from
um the French first republic. What was
it? Yeah. Uh from Napoleon and then we
have the situation where they control a
much larger territory Louisiana
purchase. Let's see.
So this is the Louisiana purchase the
area in green massive territory that
they purchase and they more than double
in size and then they go further west
further west killing more Indians
genociding and displacing more Indians I
mean the native Americans who who they
called Indians at the time. So the
Indian removal it it really took took
took off in the in the second quarter of
the 19th century between in 1830 to
1850. Around that time there was ethnic
cleansing. There was genocide. The
Indians were the native Americans were
forced to go on these extremely long
marches, death marches. The objective is
not to go from place point A to point B.
The objective was to kill off the
population in in such a by making them
walk such large distances. that that's
what it was. So there was the Indian
removal, you had the Trail of Tears
1832, 1850 thereabouts. Yeah. Uh
ethnic cleansing, genocide, mass murder.
That's that's what what it was. Um then
there is the Alaska purchase in the
second half of the 19th century. Um the
president was Andrew Johnson and the
secretary of state was William Seard and
the purchase of Alaska from Russia was
considered to be crazy. It was called
Seward's folly, but it made a lot of
sense. If you look at things today,
Alaska is so rich in resources and it's
such a vast territory for the US to own.
So they keep keep on expanding. They
eventually they take control of the
entire coast to coast area that the
present day United States states has.
They go to war with Mexico and they take
over California and Colorado and so much
more. Right? Half of Mexico essentially
or roughly almost the takeover. They
keep expanding the territory and by by
the by around 1900 they have this
gigantic territory that's continent
sized and it's an otarchy. All the
resources you can imagine that could you
could wish to have you have it. Then
second world war it the US participates
1944 you have the Breton woods uh
situation where the US dollar is made
the global dominant currency the reserve
currency in the world and then the rest
of the history you know. So that's how
the US did it from the 1600s all the way
to till today. And now they will expand
into space. That's how you do it. You
need to have huge ambition. You need to
have a huge appetite for risk. And
that's how you become a superpower. Not
through action, not through not through
slogans, through massive action and by
taking massive risks and by having the
the the ability to stomach big losses.
Right? That's what you need. That's how
the US has become what it has become.
Okay. Uh Amisha Mishra says, "Why is
Trump's evangel why does Trump's
evangelical base want him to send troops
to Nigeria?" Rush says, "Your views on
Trump wanting Nigeria to warning Nigeria
about the persecution of Christians by
extremists. What is really the game and
why is the US getting involved in
Nigeria?"
See um Trump's base the MAGA base is
many of them are evangelicals you know
conservatives and Christians and all
that and
Christianity is kind of a declining
religion in the west it's it's you know
going out of vogue in Europe definitely
even in the US a significant amount of
the population no longer believes in
Christianity so the evangelical base
wants to maintain its foothold wherever
they have it and about slightly less
than half of Nigeria is Christian and
obviously you have the situation in
Nigeria where the government isn't able
to control much of the territory in the
north and you have Boo Haram that is
this terrorist organization that kills
Christians Christians um they've been
doing it for a long time and that's why
[clears throat]
uh that's why Trump uh has warned
Nigeria about to do something otherwise
he will uh intervene. So look, foreign
policy is an outgrowth of your domestic
policy and you have to appease your
voters and that's why you have to ensure
that they they are happy and that's why
Trump has issued issued this warning to
Nigeria. Nigeria is not going against US
wishes. Nigeria is not doing anything
that will offend the US. Nigeria's
economic policy, foreign policy, etc. is
is all in line with the United States
wishes just like every other nation
essentially in Africa. But the Nigerian
government is not able to control Boohh
Haram. So maybe the US may get involved
just to pleate
the conservative voter base of the
Republican party and the the MAGA
people. Right.
Sunmoon08 says, "Do you think viral AI
videos about Indian lack of civic sense
are coming from the CCP? I don't see
them bashing Pakistanis or Bangladeshes
for these. Totally weird. It's
definitely artificially engineered. All
these viral AI videos about yeah Indians
doing whatever. Yeah, very some people
find it very offensive and they
obviously are intended to offend right
so these are most of these videos are
are AI generated videos.
The question is where does it come from?
Look does Pakistan have the AI
capability to do this? They don't. The
Chinese do of course today the if you're
Pakistani you can you can take a
subscription to an AI system maybe what
is it? Chat GPT. Chat GPT. Does it make
videos? I'm not sure. I'm sure there are
other other AI tools that allow you to
generate videos. I'm sure many of these
AI tools don't allow you to generate
offensive videos, but I'm sure that
there are some that do. So, maybe it's
coming mainly from the CCP, maybe from
China mostly, maybe also from Pakistan.
So, you can create these bot farms. You
know, you see this bookshelf behind me.
This one, you can have bookshelves. You
can have shells full of racks of mobile
phones, a,000 2,000 of these in one one
rack. And each of these mobile phones
will have one account, a bot account,
and you can create mayhem through that.
You can push all kinds of propaganda
narratives using VPNs, using whatever.
And you can create a certain image of a
nation, a certain narrative of a nation.
If you push out hundreds of such videos
every day, thousands of such videos
every day, then eventually people start
believing that India is a very backward,
very dirty, etc. nation. And to some
extent these problems do exist in India
but not to the extent that those AI
generated videos are are portraying
right so I can't say for sure where this
is coming from but definitely China and
Pakistan are the two major suspects in
this more China than Pakistan and this
has had the effect of creating
successfully creating a narrative about
India. It has succeeded right today. You
see a tremendous amount of hatred
towards Indians on social media coming
from the west. But the the sparks were
lit from outside the west, most likely
China and possibly even Pakistan.
Okay, last question for today from the
comments. Real painter says, "What's the
geopolitical significance of the Bagram
air base?" Okay, let's take a look at
Bagram. Let's go to the map and let's go
to Bagram. Let's uh change the
orientation of the map. We come to the
subcontinent. We go north of Kabul.
So let's go into the satellite imagery
and just north of Kabul, a few 30, 40,
50 km away, you have Bram. And you can
see the air base from space. There we
have it. This is Bagram. It's massive.
It's a massive air base as you can see.
And you can see it's not just the the
two runways that you see, but it's like
an entire city that's built around these
runways. It's like a fully equipped,
fully functional, self-controlled,
self-contained
military city. The US when they operated
Bagram Air Base, they were able to
station about 30,000 troops here. So you
can imagine how massive it is. And uh if
you look at the length of the runways,
okay, let's let's quickly take a rough
look at the length of the runway, it's
about 3 km, 3 km, the large runway, and
there's a smaller one that is about 2.9
or whatever kilometers. Let's see. Let's
measure that quickly. What is it? 2.9
something km. So, two massive runways
that can accommodate any kind of
aircraft, no matter how large, how heavy
it is. Two runways. And then we have
this entire massive military complex all
around it. Uh they have hospitals, they
have trauma centers, they have
intelligence gathering u you know
facilities, there are barracks, there
are hardened shelters for various kinds
of aircraft. So much more everything you
can want in an air base. You have in
Bram. It was built by the Soviets but it
was used by the Americans. And right now
it is obviously a sovereign Afghan
territory and it is under the control of
the Afghan government, the Taliban
government. And the US wants this air
base now. They want it back even though
it's not there. So why is it important?
What's the strategic significance? So
zoom out. Let's go to the to the map
itself. Zoom out and you will see that
this lies in a very interesting
neighborhood. If you are in Bram and if
you have all those surveillance
capabilities, then you can keep an eye
on Pakistan, you can keep an eye on
Northern India, you can keep an eye on
uh the the western part of Chinese
occupied territory, you can keep an eye
on Central Asia, you can obviously keep
an eye on what's happening in Iran, you
can project power in a massive way
across all these countries.
And you can even keep an eye on Russia
to some extent and and and territories
that Russia considers to be part of its
exclusive sphere of influence.
Um and Bagram has historically been
considered to be the air base of
empires. First the Soviet empire and now
later the US empire and when the US
withdrew from Bram it was kind of you
know the US lost some prestige by giving
up this massive air base. There is no
comparable air base in the entire
region. So that's the geopolitical
significance of Bagram. You can keep an
eye on China. You can if you control
Bram, you can control the whole of
Afghanistan. You can uh see Afghanistan
is very important. Why is it important?
Because it's it's at the crossroads
between east and west. It's at the it's
the northernmost part of the Indian
subcontinent. Um it's the it's the
gateway to Central Asia. If you are in
the subcontinent, it's also between
China and and West Asia, between uh the
subcontinent and central Asia and it
obviously is in Afghanistan which itself
is strategically important because of
the incredible wealth of resources you
know mineral and other resources that
Afghanistan has. So overall if you look
at all this Bram becomes tremendously
important from a strategic and
geopolitical geostrategic perspective.
That's the significance of the Bagram
Air Base and that brings me to the end
of the questions I have selected for
today. Now let's take a look at what
questions we have in the live chat. I
can see some people have taken super
chats. Well, okay, let me deal with
those super chats. Let me answer those
and that then we will end this live
stream. Susan Batwaj says, "There we
have it." Well, there we have it, sir.
Thank you so much. [laughter] Thank you
so much, sir. There we indeed have it.
Appreciate it, sir. Appreciate it very
much. James, my dear friend James says,
"Look at the status of Himalayan towns,
ugly and bad. Look at our alpine towns
glowing and shining. Indians are not
grand at winter sports as well." Well,
actually, James, if you look at
Himalayan towns, they are not that ugly.
If you go to the Himalayan parts of
India, at least there you have a sparer
population density, lower population
density and the towns are in a better
shape compared to the metropolitan parts
of India. and and some parts in the some
some
parts of the Indian Himalayas are really
picturesque, really pretty. So obviously
you can't compare Indian Himalayan towns
with let's say Aenzel or the Valet
region of Switzerland or the Alpine
parts of Europe definitely because those
are first world countries and we still
are quite aren't that right but things
are improving um and there's tremendous
natural beauty in the Indian Himalayas.
The Indian Himalayas are are very
different from the Alps in Europe. The
Alps, if you visit, the mountains look
tame. The mountains look tame. You come
to the Himalayas, the mountains look
wild, untamed, rugged. Nothing tame
about the Himalayas, right? Very
different character. But I I know what
you mean. We're not talking about the
natural beauty here. We're talking about
the situation, the way the towns,
cities, etc. are maintained. And
obviously, there's a disparity between
India and Europe, India and the West.
And that is something we Indians have to
acknowledge. But I I think I'm pretty
sure things are improving. If you go to
for example Ladak, if you go to Lei and
then now you have a new airport coming
up in Lelay, I hope it would have become
operational or would be on the verge of
becoming operational and you can see
progress. You can see development all of
that happening in India. So it's not
like we are just sitting where we are.
We are making progress and eventually
next 20 years things will be very
different. So I appreciate you James for
pointing out these uh these uh
situations.
And yeah, I appreciate you sir. 6P70
Delta says, "Have you read the news of
RAF getting Indian instructors?" Royal
Air Force from white man's burden to
brown man's burden or James would not be
happy. I feel well I have not seen this
news but let's quickly check it out. RAF
getting Indian instructors. Well, well,
well. What what is the world coming to
RAF Indian instructors? Really?
Um in reversal of colonial times IF
instructors to train UK's RAF to hawk
qualified flying instructors from India
will be based on angle aid for up to
three years
part of a new defense cooperation
agreement between the UK and India.
First time since World War II that IF
pilots will train RAF pilots. Well well
very interesting. Good to see that.
White man's burden to bronze man brown
man's burden. Well times change. See we
have to remember historically for the
most of history for the longest part of
history India has been the world's
dominant economy and the world's
dominant technological power the oldest
civilization and the first civilization
to become fully maritime fully
industrialized fully urbanized. So we
are slowly
working towards
reattaining our natural position in the
world and these whatever we see here
that's signs and symptoms of that
happening and that's why there is push
back against that and that's natural
and we have to strive harder.
6P70 Delta says many so-called experts
say now say that Ukraine
has shown that Russian weapons are
trash. If that's the case then why are
NATO increasing their defense spending
significantly? Um what's my opinion on
one rupee $1 equal to three rupees by
2030 prediction? Okay, first of all uh
yeah it's it's kind of reasonable it's
kind of laughable that uh when people
say that you know you can show that
Russian weapons are trash. If Russian
weapons are were trash then Russia would
have lost the war. If Russian weapons
would crash then then the US would not
force the NATO nations to increase their
their defense expenditure by by 100%
right by 2030 to double their their
budgetary allocation to defense by 2030
and so much more it would not be the
case. Russian weapons are battle tested
they are robust and they are getting the
job done for Russia. So first of all
there's that. What's my opinion on
dollar one one becoming rupees 3 by 2030
prediction? I am not aware of this
prediction and uh yeah I'm not aware of
it. I've not studied it so I can't
really say. I think it is a very very
steep target
but I will be happy if that happens but
I am I have not studied this so I can't
say. Taran Taran is a new member. Well
thank you very much Taran and let us all
welcome Taran to membership. I really
appreciate it Tan really appreciate
that. Hershel Singla says Palestinian
foreign minister Varsen says India
potential bridge builder for peace in
Gaza. Also we saw how Trump deals with
Putin. Many think India can play a role
there also. Are these too far-fetched?
Well, from the the way I see it,
Palestine is not our problem. Gaza is
not our problem. But if we can use our
good offices in bringing about a
peaceful resolution to whatever is
happening there, which is obviously very
nasty and terrible from a humanitarian
perspective, then obviously we'll be
happy to oblige. If the Palestinians are
are supportive or or or if they are
desirous of India
let's say playing a role in u in
building in bringing about peace in Gaza
and if the Israelis also are in
agreement then I'm perfectly in favor of
India doing that. So India certainly can
potentially play a role. We are on good
terms with very good terms with Israel,
no question. And we also have good good
relations with the with the
Palestinians, right? We have always
supported the Palestinian cause uh for
for a Palestinian nation. That's how our
position has been historically. So as
such, we are uniquely positioned to play
a constructive role. Uh it certainly can
happen if both sides so desire with the
blessings of the bigger brother, the
United States. Basar Kayatwal says,
"Happy birthday in advance. Thank you
very much, sir. Thank you. All the love
and support in the world for you.
Grateful you are spending these hours
before birthday with us. See you soon in
Jaipur. Hope you and your family are
doing amazing. Sunrocket. Thank you so
much. So thank you so much. I'm doing
great and thank you so much for the
wishes and uh yep I'll be there in
Jaipur and I look forward to seeing you
Basar and everybody else whoever comes
there. I'll be very pleased to meet you
all and maybe have some interesting
interactions. I look forward to it.
Thank you. Sunil Bunel says China built
build built a thorium reactor. What
about India?
Well, until a few years ago, India was
supposed to have the world's most
advanced podium research program. We
have this uh three-stage nuclear
program. We are at the end of the first
stage and we we are potentially stepping
into the second stage. I've spoken about
this in detail in the past. Um what
about India? Like like I said with space
we have the capabilities, we have the
engineers, we have the knowhow, we have
the scientists but do we have the
ambition? Does the government have the
ambition? I know that we are building
more nuclear reactors and all but
thorium. So we have to get through the
second stage to reach the thorium stage.
The thorium stage is essentially the
third third stage. We need more drive.
We need a surge.
what we can do over the next 10 years
why don't we do it in the next one year
or three years
for that we need drive we need ambition
we need that thing right we don't seem
to have it what can I say what can I say
we have the world's largest thorium
reserves 25 to 30% of the entire world's
thorium reserves are in India and
they're just sitting there
what can I say no Sony thank you very
much sir no question but yeah thank you
very I really appreciate your
contribution to the channel. Thank you.
No.
Karthik says, "Grochipedia gives
unbiased factual answers on Ram Mander
God riots and so on. Have I tried? I
have not tried it but I've seen some
screenshots here and there on on on X on
Twitter. It's clear that Gipedia is far
better than Wikipedia. But is it really
unbiased? I will have to look see about.
I am very skeptical that it's going to
be completely unbiased. It's going to
have some subtle biases for sure baked
into it. But it is no question about it.
It's far better than Wikipedia.
Wikipedia is just slanted open overt
blatant slant against India. No
question. I I always keep saying right
whenever I open up a Wikipedia page for
for the sake of uh quickness
I always say that statutory warning
Wikipedia is not necessarily a good
source of information reliable source of
information especially when it comes to
India and Indian history probably is
better but it will still have some
subtle inbuilt biases I guarantee that
but I'll have to see it for for for
myself and maybe I'll take some
screenshots and show you once that
happens when once I'm able to do
Amisha says, "Happy birthday, sir. God
bless you." Thank you so much, ma'am.
Thank you so much. God bless you, too. I
really appreciate the wishes and and
your viewership and everything else.
Thank you so much. Satellite
says, "How much GPUs, how many GPUs does
it take to run one AI
AI? [laughter]
There's no GPUs inside of me." Um, yeah.
Anyway, [laughter]
nice funny question. I appreciate that.
I appreciate. Thank you very much. Dave
says, "Starlink is signing deals with
our states now to provide satellite
based internet. What are my views? Why
is the government of India allowing it?"
Happy birthday, sir in advance. Thank
you very much. Why is the government of
India allowing it? I do not know why
India the government of India is
allowing this. In my opinion, we should
not allow this. I can't speak on behalf
of the government of India as to why
this is being allowed.
But um I am of the firm opinion that
they should not be allowed.
That's all I can say. I can't answer
your question because I'm not in the
government of India and I'm not privy to
the thinking that goes on behind the
scenes that gives rise to these
decisions. All right. 6p70 delta says
this prediction of dollar 1 equal to
rupees 3 was made by Dr. Ankit. Okay.
Noted but I am not aware of it. So I I
can't really uh comment about it because
I've not studied it. I've not uh seen
this. Anyway, thank you for the
information. Satellite says happy
birthday sir. Thank you so much
satellite. Thank you so much everybody
else. This brings me to the end of this
live stream. Thank you very much. Um may
be bless me.
[laughter]
Okay.
All right. So thank you so much. This
brings me to to the end of this live
stream and this weekend I want to be
doing live streams because I will be in
Jaipur but regular programming resumes
next week onwards and I shall put out
some clips in the intervening period.
Thank you so much everybody and I look
forward to seeing you in the next one.
Keep learning, keep asking questions,
keep raising your standards. See you in
the next one. Thank you very much. Take
care. Those of you who are coming to
Jaipur, I'll see you there. Everybody
else, see you soon. Bye-bye.